<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="grc">Περὶ τῶν μετονομαζομένων καὶ ὧν ἐνεκὰ μετονομάζονται</title>
<title>About Those Whose Names Are Changed and Why They Have Their Names Changed</title>
<author>Philo of Alexandria</author>
<editor>Francis Henry Colson (1857-1943)</editor>
<editor>George Herbert Whitaker (1847-1930)<note>https://www.hup.harvard.edu/results-list.php?author=3729</note></editor>
<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
<name>Gregory Crane</name>
<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>

</respStmt>
<funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
</titleStmt>
<extent/>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
    <date type="release" when="2023-06-23">Perseus 5.0</date>
    <idno type="filename">tlg0018.tlg021.perseus-grc3.xml</idno>
    <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
    </availability>
</publicationStmt>

    <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
            <biblStruct>
                <monogr>
                    <author>Philo of Alexandria</author>
                    <title>Philo in Ten Volumes</title>
                    <editor>Francis Henry Colson (1857-1943)</editor>
                    <editor>George Herbert Whitaker (1847-1930)<note>https://www.hup.harvard.edu/results-list.php?author=3729</note></editor>
                    <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                        <date>1934</date>
                    </imprint>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
                </monogr>
                <ref target="https://ryanfb.github.io/loebolus-data/L275.pdf">Github</ref>
            </biblStruct>
        </listBibl>
    </sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction method="silent">
<p>optical character recognition</p>
</correction>
</editorialDecl>
    <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)"
            replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
            <p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
    </refsDecl>
<!-- <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="section" n="chunk"/>å
</refsDecl>-->
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>
<div type="edition" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0018.tlg018.colson_eng" xml:lang="grc">
<pb n="143"/>
<head>About Those Whose Names are Changed and Why They Have Their Names Changed</head>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="1"/> “Abraham became ninety-nine years old and the

Lord was seen by Abraham and said to him, ‘I am thy God’” (Gen. xvii. 1). Nine plus ninety is next neighbour to a hundred, the number irradiated by the self-taught nature Isaac who is joy, the best of the good emotions.
<note n="5.143.a">Here used in the strict Stoic sense of reasonable forms of πάθος. See note on <hi rend="italic">Quod Det.</hi> 120. So also in <hi rend="italic">De Mig.</hi> 157, <hi rend="italic">De Cong.</hi> 36, and below, §§ 131, 188.</note>
  For Isaac is born to Abraham when a hundred years old.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p> A hundred also represents

the first-fruits given to the priests by the Tribe of Levi. For when the Levites receive the tenths they offer from them, just as though they were their own produce, other tenths in which we find the hundred (Num. xviii. 26). For ten is a symbol of progress and a hundred of perfection. Now he who is in the intermediate stage is always pressing forward to the summit, employing the gifts with which nature has blessed him, and it is by such a one that Moses tells us that the Lord of all was seen.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p> Yet

do not suppose that the vision was presented to the eyes of the body. They see only the objects of sense and those are composite, brimful of corruptibility, while the divine is uncompounded and incorruptible. It is the eye of the soul which receives the presentation of the divine vision.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p> Moreover what the eyes



<pb n="145"/>

of the body behold they apprehend through the cooperation of light, and light is something different from either the seer or the thing seen, whereas what the soul beholds it beholds by its own agency without the assistance of any other. For the conceptions of the mind are a light to themselves.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p> Our learning

of the sciences follows the same rule. The mind applies its eye which never closes or sleeps to the principles and conclusions set before it and sees them by no borrowed but a genuine light which shines forth from itself.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p> And so when you hear that God

was seen by man, you must think that this takes place without the light which the senses know, for what belongs to mind can be apprehended only by the mental powers. And God is the fountain of the purest radiance, and so when He reveals Himself to a soul the rays He puts forth are free from all shadow and of intense brightness.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="2"/> Do not however suppose that the Existent

which truly exists is apprehended by any man; for we have in us no organ by which we can envisage it, neither in sense, for it is not perceptible by sense, nor yet in mind. So Moses the explorer of nature which lies beyond our vision, Moses who, as the divine oracles tell us, entered into the darkness
<note n="5.145.a">See App. p. 586.</note>
  (Ex. xx. 21), by which figure they indicate existence invisible and incorporeal, searched everywhere and into everything in his desire to see clearly and plainly Him, the object of our much yearning, Who alone is good.




<pb n="147"/>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>And when there was no sign of finding aught, not

even any semblance of what he hoped for, in despair of learning from others, he took refuge with the Object of his search Itself and prayed in these words: “Reveal Thyself to me that I may see Thee with knowledge” (Ex. xxxiii. 13). And yet he fails to gain his object.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p> To know what lies below the Existent, things material and immaterial alike, is a most ample gift even for the best sort among mortals, as God judges, for we read, “Thou shalt see what is behind

Me, but My face thou shalt not see” (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> 23). It means that all below the Existent, things material and immaterial alike, are available to apprehension even if they are not all actually apprehended as yet, but He alone by His very nature cannot be seen.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><p> And why should we wonder that the Existent cannot

be apprehended by men when even the mind in each of us is unknown to us?</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11"><p> For who knows the essential nature of the soul, that mystery which has bred numberless contentions among the sophists who propound opinions contrary to each other or even totally and generically opposed?It is a logical

consequence that no personal name even can be properly assigned to the truly Existent. Note that when the prophet desires to know what he must answer to those who ask about His name He says “I am He that is” (Ex iii. 14), which is equivalent to “My nature is to be, not to be spoken.”</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12"><p> Yet that

the human race should not totally lack a title to give to the supreme goodness He allows them to use by licence of language, as though it were His proper

<pb n="149"/>

name,
<note n="5.149.a">Philo seems to mix in this passage two somewhat different uses of the grammatical term κύριον ὄνομα: (1) a noun used in its literal or strict sense, opposed to metaphorical or loose usage (ἐν καταχρήσει, see note on <hi rend="italic">De Cher.</hi> 121); (2) a proper or personal name.</note>
  the title of Lord God of the three natural orders, teaching, perfection, practice,
<note n="5.149.b">See App. p. 586.</note>
  which are symbolized in the records as Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. For this He says is “My age-long name,” belonging as it were to the age of human existence, not to that when age as yet was not, “a memorial” too, not set, that is, beyond memory or apprehension, and again “to generations” (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> 15), not to beings that were never generated.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13"><p> For those who are born into

mortality must needs have some substitute for the divine name, so that they may approach if not the fact at least the name of supreme excellence and be brought into relation with it. And this is shown by the oracle proclaimed as from the mouth of the Ruler of all in which He says that no proper name of Him has been revealed to any. “I was seen,” He says, “of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, being their God, and My name of ‘Lord’ I did not reveal to them” (Ex. vi. 3). For when the transposition
<note n="5.149.c">Philo seems to mean that while το ὄνομά μου κύριον will naturally mean “my name κύριος,” the text should (or perhaps may also) be regarded as an “hyperbaton” or “unusual order” of ὄνομά μου τὸ κύριον, “my proper name” For the technical use of the term see App. pp. 586 f.</note>
  is reset in the proper order it will run thus, “My proper name I did not reveal to thee,” but, He implies, only the substitute, and that for reasons already mentioned.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14"><p> So

impossible to name indeed is the Existent that not even the Potencies who serve Him tell us a proper name. Thus after the wrestling-bout in which the Man




<pb n="151"/>

of Practice engaged in his quest of virtue, he says to the unseen master,
<note n="5.151.a">I understand ἀοράτῳ, for which Mangey would substitute ἀρρήτῳ, to refer to the wrestling of the story taking place at night and stopping at dawn. Wendland suspected ἐπιστάτῃ and proposed παλαιστῇ, but Philo conceives of the angel rather as a master of the contest (ἀγωνοθέτης) training his pupil by wrestling with him; <hi rend="italic">cf. De Som.</hi> i. 129.</note>
  “Announce to me Thy name,” and he said “Why dost thou ask this my name?” (Gen. xxxii. 29), and he refuses to tell his personal and proper name. “It is enough for thee,” he means, “to profit through my benediction, but as for names, those symbols which indicate created beings, look not for them in the case of imperishable natures.”

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="3"/> Think it not then a hard saying that the Highest

of all things should be unnamable when His Word has no name of its own which we can speak. And indeed if He is unnamable He is also inconceivable and incomprehensible. And so the words “The Lord was seen of Abraham” (Gen. xvii. 1) must not be understood in the sense that the Cause of all shone upon him and appeared to him, for what human mind could contain the vastness of that vision? Rather we must think of it as the manifestation of one of the Potencies which attend him, the Potency of kingship, for the title Lord betokens sovereignty and kingship.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16"><p> While our mind pursued

the airy speculations of the Chaldeans it ascribed to the world powers of action which it regarded as causes. But when it migrated from the Chaldean creed it recognized that the world had for its charioteer and pilot a Ruler Whose sovereignty was presented to it in vision.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17"><p> And therefore the words are “The

Lord (not “The Existent”) was seen of him,” as though it would say, The king has been manifested, king indeed from the first, but hitherto unrecognized


<pb n="153"/>

by the soul, which so long unschooled has not remained in ignorance for ever but has received the vision of the Sovereignty which rules over all that is.<milestone unit="section" n="18"/>
But the Sovereign when manifested

confers a still higher gift on him who sees and hears him. He says to him, “I am thy God.” Which indeed amongst all this multitude of created things does not have Thee for its god? I might ask. But His interpreting word will shew me that He does not here speak of the world of which doubtless He is Creator and God, but of human souls which do not in His eyes deserve to be cared for all alike.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19"><p> His will

is to be called the Lord and Master of the bad, the God of those who are on the way to betterment, but of the best and most perfect both at once God and Lord. For instance, when He has set Pharaoh before us as the crowning example of impiety He never calls Himself his God but gives that name to wise Moses, “Behold I give thee as god to Pharaoh” (Ex. vii. 1). But He often names Himself as Lord in the oracles which He gives.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20"><p> We find such utterances as these, “These things saith the Lord”

(Ex. vii. 17), and at the beginning of His speech
<note n="5.153.a">i.e. at the beginning of the speech to which the earlier quotation, “Behold I give thee etc.,” belongs. But as another quotation has intervened, this is rather forced. I should like to read ἐν ἀρχῇ, καί, i.e. “as an opening phrase.”</note>
  “The Lord spake unto Moses, saying, ‘I am the Lord, speak unto Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, all that I speak unto thee’” (Ex. vi.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21"><p> 29). And Moses says to Pharaoh, “When I go forth from the city I

will spread out my hands to the Lord, and the sounds shall cease and the hail and the rain shall not be, that thou mayest know that to the Lord belongs the earth” (that is all the bodily earth-compounded frame), “and thou” (that is the mind which the body


<pb n="155"/>

carries with it) “and thy servants” (that is the several thoughts which form its guard), “for I know that ye have not yet feared the Lord” (Ex. ix. 29), meaning that Lord who is not merely so-called but is Lord in very truth.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22"><p> For none that is created is

truly a lord, though he be invested with a rule that spreads from pole to pole.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23"><p> Only the Uncreated is truly ruler, and he who lives in fear and awe under that Ruler’s government receives a prize of truest value in His reproofs, while he who despises them has before him nothing but to perish miserably.So then He is shown to be the Lord of the foolish in

that He holds over them the terrors that are proper to the sovereign. Of those who are on the way to betterment He is called in scripture God, as in this present passage, “I am thy God,” or “I am thy God, increase and multiply” (Gen. xxxv. 11). Of the perfect He is both Lord and God as in the Decalogue “I am thy Lord God” (Ex. xx. 2), and elsewhere “The Lord God of your fathers” (Deut. iv.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24"><p> 1), for it is His will that the wicked man should

be under His sway as his Lord, and thus with awe and groaning feel the fear of the Master hanging over him; that the man of progress should be benefited by Him as God and thus through those kindnesses reach perfection; that the perfect should be guided by Him as Lord and benefited by Him as God. For through the one he remains free from lapses, through the other he is most surely God’s man.This is best shown in Moses’ case.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25"><p> “This is the

blessing,” we read, “which Moses gave, the man of God” (Deut. xxxiii. 1). To what a glorious, what a



<pb n="157"/>

holy exchange is he promoted that in return for God’s protecting care he should give himself to God.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26"><p> But do not suppose that God becomes man’s in the

same way that man becomes God’s, for a man is God’s as His possession, God is man’s to be his glory and assistance. If thou wouldst have God as thy heart’s portion, first become thyself a portion worthy for Him to take, and that thou shalt become if thou escape such faults as are thine own handiwork and come of free will.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="4"/> We should remember this also that the words

“I am thy God” are used by licence of language and not in their proper sense, for the Existent considered as existent is not relative. He is full of Himself and is sufficient for Himself. It was so before the creation of the world, and is equally so after the creation of all that is.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28"><p> He cannot change nor alter

and needs nothing else at all, so that all things are His but He Himself in the proper sense belongs to none. But the Potencies which He has projected into creation to benefit what He has framed are in some cases spoken of as in a sense relative,
<note n="5.157.a">See App. p. 587.</note>
  such as





<pb n="159"/>

the kingly and the beneficial, for a king is a king of someone and a benefactor the benefactor of someone, while the subject of the kingship and the recipient of the benefit is necessarily something different.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29"><p> Akin to these two is the creative Potency

called God, because through this the Father who is its begetter and contriver made
<note n="5.159.a">θεός being derived from τίθημι; see note on <hi rend="italic">De Conf.</hi> 137.</note>
  the universe, so that “I am thy God” is equivalent to “I am the Maker and Artificer.”</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30"><p> And the greatest gift we can have

is to have Him for our Architect, Who was also the Architect of the whole world, for He did not form the soul of the bad, since wickedness is at enmity with Him, and in framing the soul which is in the intermediate stage He was not the sole agent according to the holiest of men, Moses, since such a soul would surely admit like wax the different qualities of noble and base.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31"><p> And therefore we read,

“Let us make man after our image” (Gen. i. 26), so that according as the wax received the bad or the noble impress it should appear to be the handiwork of others or of Him Who is the framer of the noble and the good alone.
<note n="5.159.b"><hi rend="italic">Cf. De Op.</hi> 72 ff., <hi rend="italic">De Conf.</hi> 168 ff., <hi rend="italic">De Fug.</hi> 68 ff.</note>
  Surely then he is a man of virtue to whom God says “I am thy God,” for he has God alone for his maker without the co-operation of others.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32"><p> At the same time
<note n="5.159.c">Or “indeed here with other lessons” (ἅμα), i.e. those of §§ 18 and 28.</note>
  Moses teaches us here

by implication the doctrine which he so often
<note n="5.159.d">In the other texts where God says “We” (see <hi rend="italic">De Conf.</hi> 16) and Gen. xlviii. 15, 16 (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>. 181).</note>
  lays down that God is the maker of the wise and good only. And all that company
<note n="5.159.e">See App. p. 587.</note>
  have voluntarily stripped themselves of the external goods which are so abundantly supplied to us, and further have despised what is dear to the flesh.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33"><p> Fine, lusty and athletic



<pb n="161"/>

are those who use the body as a menace to the soul. Pale, wasted and withered, so to speak, are the children of discipline. They have made over the bodily muscles to serve the powers of the soul and in fact are resolved into a single form, that of soul, and become unbodied minds.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34"><p> Naturally then the earthly

element is destroyed and dissolved when the mind in all its powers has a fixed purpose to be well pleasing to God. But that kind is rare and hardly to be found, though that such should be is not impossible. This is shown by the oracle vouchsafed about Enoch. “Enoch was well pleasing to God and was not found”
<note n="5.161.a">E.V. “Enoch walked with God; and he was not; for God took him” (LXX μετέθηκε). For “found” see App. p. 587.</note>
  (Gen. v.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35"><p> 24), for where

could one search and find this good thing, what seas should he cross, what islands, what continents should he visit? Shall he look for it among the Greeks or the barbarians?</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36"><p> Indeed are there not still among

the disciples of philosophy some who say that a wise man is non-existent
<note n="5.161.b">See App. pp. 587 f.</note>
  and therefore wisdom also? None, they say, from the beginning of man’s creation up to the life of to-day has been held to be completely free from fault, for absolute happiness is impossible to one who is imprisoned in the mortal body.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37"><p> Whether

these statements are true we will inquire at the proper occasion. At present we will accept the text and say that wisdom is indeed something which exists, and so too is the lover of wisdom, the sage, but, though he exists, we who are evil fail to see him, for good cannot keep company with bad.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38"><p> Therefore

we are told that “he was not found,” this type of character which was well pleasing to God, meaning



<pb n="163"/>

doubtless that though actually existing he was hidden from us and shunned our company. And to confirm this we read that he was “translated”
<note n="5.163.a">As E.V. in Hebrews xi. 5.</note>
  (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>), that is, changed his abode and journeyed as an emigrant from the mortal life to the immortal.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="5"/> These are men inspired with heaven-sent madness,

men who have gone out into the wild. But there are others who have followed a tame and gentle wisdom,
<note n="5.163.b"><hi rend="italic">Cf. Quis Rerum</hi>127.</note>
  and such are both eminent in the practice of piety and do not despise human things. This is attested by the oracle in which it is said to Abraham, with God as speaker, “Be well pleasing before Me” (Gen. xvii. 1), that is, “be well pleasing not to Me only but to My works, while I as judge watch and survey thee.”</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40"><p> For if you honour parents or show

mercy to the poor or do kindness to your friends or defend your country or observe with care your duties to all men in general, you will surely be well pleasing to all with whom you have to do, but also well pleasing before God. For He with an eye that never sleeps beholds all things, and what is good He summons to Himself and approves with special favour.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41"><p> And therefore the Practiser in his prayer will show

us the same truth. “The God,” he says, “to whom my fathers were well pleasing,” and adds “before Him” (Gen. xlviii. 15) to show us the difference in fact between being pleasing “to Him” and “before Him.” The latter embraces both kinds of well pleasing, the former is confined to one only.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42"><p> And

so Moses in his Exhortations
<note n="5.163.c">See note on <hi rend="italic">De Fug.</hi> 170.</note>
  charges them in these words: “Thou shalt do what is well pleasing before the Lord thy God” (Deut. xii. 28), meaning do such things as shall be worthy to appear before God, and when seen to be approved by Him, and such

<pb n="165"/>

deeds as these commonly extend to our fellow-men.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43"><p> It was this thought which prompted

Moses when he wove the tabernacle, dividing its precincts into two, and set a curtain between the parts to distinguish the inner from the outer (Ex. xxvi. 33); when too he gilded the sacred ark which holds the laws both within and without (Ex. xxv. 10), and gave the high priest two robes, the linen robe to be worn within, the many-coloured one with the long skirt to be worn outside (Ex. xxviii. 4, Lev. vi.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44"><p> 10). These and the like are symbols of a soul which in

inward things is undefiled towards God and in outward things is pure towards the world of our senses and human life. And so those were fitting words which were said to the victorious wrestler when he was about to be crowned with garlands of triumph. For “Thou hast been strong with God and mighty with men” (Gen. xxxii. 28) were the words which proclaimed his victory.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45"><p> To win honour in both spheres, in

our duty both towards the uncreated and the created, requires no petty mind, but one which stands in very truth midway between the world and God. And in sum the man of worth should follow in the steps of God, for the Ruler and Father of all cares for His creatures.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46"><p> We all know that before the

creation of the world God was sufficient unto Himself and that after the creation He remained the same, unchanged. Why then did He make the things which were not? Why, save because He was good
<note n="5.165.a">See App. p. 588.</note>
  and bountiful? Shall not then we His slaves




<pb n="167"/>

follow our Master with profoundest awe and reverence for Him Who is the Cause, yet not forgetting the calls of our common humanity?
<note n="5.167.a">For the general thought of this passage with the same illustration from the two robes and the words of Gen. xxxii, 28 cf. the fuller exposition in <hi rend="italic">De Ebr</hi>. 80–87.</note>


</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="6"/> After saying “Be well pleasing before Me”

He adds further “and become blameless.’’ This is in close sequence to the preceding. “Best it is,” He means, “to set your hand to excellence and thus be well pleasing, but failing this at least abstain from sins and thus escape blame.” For positively righteous conduct
<note n="5.167.b">See App. p. 588.</note>
  brings praise to the doer, but abstention from iniquity saves him from censure.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="48"><p> The highest prize of “well pleasing” may be won

by positive well-doing, the second, freedom from blame, by avoidance of sin. And yet perhaps for the creature of mortal kind the former is declared by Scripture to coincide with the latter. For who, as Job says, is pure from defilement, even if his life be but for one day? (Job xiv.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="49"><p> 4). Infinite indeed are

the defilements that soil the soul, which it is impossible to wash and scour away altogether. For there still remain evils which are bound up with the life of every mortal, which may well be abated but cannot be wholly destroyed.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="50"><p> Should we then seek to

find in the medley of life one who is perfectly just or wise or temperate or good in general? Be satisfied, if you do but find one who is not unjust, is not foolish, is not licentious, is not cowardly, is not altogether evil. We may be content with the overthrow of vices, and the complete acquisition of virtues is impossible for man, as we know him.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="51"><p> With good reason then did He say, “Become blameless,”



<pb n="169"/>

for He holds that freedom from sin and guilt is a great furtherance towards a happy life.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="52"><p>  And to him who has elected to live in this fashion He promises to leave a covenanted portion such as is fitting for God to give and man to receive, for He says “I will set my covenant between Me and

between thee” (Gen. xvii. 2). Now covenants are drawn up for the benefit of those who are worthy of the gift, and thus a covenant is a symbol of the grace which God has set between Himself Who proffers it and man who receives.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="53"><p> And this is the

crowning benefaction, that there is nothing between God and the soul save the virgin grace. But I have dealt with the whole subject of covenants in two treatises, and I willingly pass it over to avoid repetition, and also because I do not wish to interrupt the continuity of the discussion.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="54"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="7"/> The next words are “Abraham fell on his

face.” Ah, what else should he do, when he heard the divine promises, but know himself and the nothingness of our mortal race, and fall at the feet of Him Who stands, to show what conception he held of himself and God? He knew that God stands with place unchanged, yet moves the universal frame of creation, His own motion being the motion of self-extension (not the movement of the legs, for He is not of human form), but a motion whereby He shows His unalterable, unchanging nature.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="55"><p> He

knew that he himself is never firmly set in a stable



<pb n="171"/>

position, that he is ever subject to various changes, and that throughout his life, which is one long slipping, he trips and falls, woe to him! and how great is that fall.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="56"><p> Sometimes it is through involuntary

ignorance, sometimes through voluntary yielding to temptation, and so we read also that it was on his face that he fell. By face is meant his senses and his mind and his speech, and the gesture is little less than a loud insistent utterance. Fallen is sense, it cries, unable of itself to perceive, were it not by a dispensation of God’s saving providence set on its feet to the perception of material substances: fallen is speech, because it were unable to express in language anything that is, did not He Who framed and adjusted to harmony the instrument of the voice beat out the music of its notes, opening the mouth and giving strength to the nerves of the tongue: fallen too is the royal mind, robbed of its powers of apprehension, did not the Framer of all that lives raise it up and establish it, and planting in it far-piercing eyes, lead it to the sight of the immaterial world.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="57"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="8"/> The frame of mind which shrank from Him

and fell spontaneously won God’s high approval by thus acknowledging of the Existent that it is He alone Who stands and that all below Him are subject to change and mutation of every kind. He addresses him with an insistence which is also a call to partnership.
<note n="5.171.a">Literally “he both speaks with emphasis (or “instructs”) and gives him a share of the speech.” See App. p. 588.</note>
  “And I,” He says, “—see, My covenant is with thee” (Gen. xvii.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="58"><p> 4). The meaning suggested is to

this purport—there are very many kinds of covenant, assuring bounties and gifts to the worthy, but the highest form of covenant is “I myself.” He shews and

<pb n="173"/>

points to Himself, as far as He can be shewn Who is above all shewing, by the words “And I,” and adds, “behold my covenant,” the beginning and the fountain of all bounties is “I myself.”
</p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="59"><p>
For to some God

is wont to extend His benefactions by other means, earth, water, air, sun, moon, heaven, and other agencies not material, but to others by Himself alone, making Himself the portion of those who receive Him.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="60"><p> On these He presently bestows as their due

a different name. “Thy name shall not be called Abram (Ἀβράμ),” we read, “but Abraham (Ἀβραάμ)” (Gen. xvii. 5). Some of the quarrelsome and captious type of people who wish to attach blame where it is not due, not so much to material things as to actions andideas,
<note n="5.173.a">See note on <hi rend="italic">Quis Rerum</hi> 242.</note>
  and wage war to the death against what is holy, when they find anything which seems to them to fall short in propriety if taken literally, while really it is a symbol of the nature-truth which loves concealment, make no careful search for that truth, but disparage it and hold it up to obloquy. And this they do especially with the changes of names.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="61"><p> Not long ago I heard the scoffing and railing of a

godless and impious fellow who dared to speak thus: “Vast and extraordinary indeed are the gifts which Moses says come from the hand of the Ruler of all. What a boon He is supposed to have provided by adding a single letter, an alpha, and again by another addition of a rho, for He &lt;turned Abram (Ἀβράμ) into Abraham (Ἀβραάμ) by doubling the alpha, and&gt; Abraham’s wife Sarai (Σάρα) into Sarah (Σάρρα) by




<pb n="175"/>

doubling the rho.” And in a sneering way he ran over the list of such cases without a moment’s pause.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="62"><p> Well, it was not long before he paid the penalty

which his wicked folly called for. For a slight and trivial cause he hastened to hang himself, and thus even a clean death was denied to the unclean miscreant.

<milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="9"/> It is only right that to prevent any other falling a victim to the same errors we should eradicate misgivings of this sort
<note n="5.175.a">This use of ὑπονοίας is strange, though Wend.’s suggestion of τὰς &lt;τοιαύτας&gt; ὑπ. or Mangey’s τὰς &lt;κακὰς&gt; ὑπ. would make it more natural. See App. p. 589.</note>
  by resorting to the truths of nature and shewing that what we thus read is worthy of our most earnest consideration.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="63"><p> Letters,

whether vowels or consonants and the parts of speech in general, are not the gifts of God’s grace, seeing that when He created the plants and animals He summoned them to man as their ruler, set apart by Him from them all in virtue of his knowledge, that he might give each kind their distinguishing names. “Everything,” he says, “which Adam called them, that was their name” (Gen. ii.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="64"><p> 19). If God did not

think fit to assign names even in their completed form, but committed the task to a man of wisdom, the founder of the human race, is it proper to suppose that parts of names or syllables or single letters, not merely vocal vowels but mute consonants, were added and altered by Himself, and a gift and pre-eminent benefaction alleged to be conferred thereby? It is quite impossible.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="65"><p> Such changes of name are signs
<note n="5.175.b">See App. p. 589.</note>
  of

moral values, the signs small, sensible, obvious, the values great, intelligible, hidden. And these values are found in noble verities, in unerring and pure notions,



<pb n="177"/>

and in soul-betterments.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="66"><p>  The proof of this is easy, starting from the change of name here before us, for Abram is interpreted as “uplifted

father,” Abraham as “elect father of sound.”
<note n="5.177.a">The interpretation of Abram and Abraham has already been given in <hi rend="italic">De Cher</hi>. 4 f. and <hi rend="italic">De Gig</hi>. 62 f. That of Sarai and Sarah in <hi rend="italic">De Cher</hi>. 5 f.</note>
  How the two differ we shall understand more clearly if we first discover the meaning of each.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="67"><p> Resorting then to

allegory we say that “uplifted” is one who rising from earth to the heights surveys the supraterrestrial, conversing with and studying the phenomena of the upper world, investigating the size of the sun and its courses, how it regulates the seasons of the year by its revolutions as it advances and retreats at the same rate of speed; one who considers also the different illuminations of the moon, its phases, its waning and waxing, and the movement of the other stars both in the fixed and the planetary order.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="68"><p> To inquire into such

matters bespeaks a soul not devoid of natural gifts or unproductive, but highly gifted and capable of engendering offspring perfect and without blemish; and therefore he called the student of the upper world “father” because he is not unproductive of wisdom.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="69"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="10"/> Such is our definition of the

meanings conveyed under the symbol of the name Abram; those conveyed by “Abraham” are such as I proceed to describe. They are three in number—“father,” “elect” and “of sound.” We say that sound stands for the uttered word, for in living creatures the instrument of sound is the vocal power. Its father is the mind, since the stream of speech issues from the understanding as its fount. The elect mind is the mind of the wise, since it contains what


<pb n="179"/>

is best.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="70"><p> So then the first set of signs delineated the

lover of learning, the meteorologist, while those just sketched reveal the wisdom-lover or rather the wise. Cease then to suppose that the Deity’s gift was a change of name, instead of a betterment of character symbolized thereby.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="71"><p> Him who was erstwhile busied

in the study of the nature of heaven—the astrologer as some call him—He summoned to a partnership in virtue and both made him and named him wise, giving to the spiritual outlook thus recast the title of Abraham, as the Hebrews would call it, and in our language, Elect Father of Sound.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="72"><p> For what purpose,

He asks, do you investigate the rhythmic movements and revolutions of the stars? Why this great leap from earth up to the realm of ether? Is it just to busy yourself in idle labour with what is there? And what good can result from all that idle busying? How will it serve to subdue the urge of pleasure, to overthrow the power of lust, to suppress fear or grief? What surgery has it for passions which agitate and confound the soul?</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="73"><p> Just as there is no use for

trees, if they are not capable of bearing fruit, so too also with nature-study, if it is not going to bring the acquisition of virtue.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="74"><p> For virtue is its fruit, and

therefore some of the ancients, comparing the study of philosophy to a field, likened the physical part to plants, the logical to the walls and fences, and the ethical to the fruit.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="75"><p>
<note n="5.179.a">See <hi rend="italic">De Agr</hi>. 14 and <hi rend="italic">Leg. All</hi>. i. 57, and notes.</note>
  They considered that the walls

round the field are built by the owners to guard the fruit and the trees grown to produce it, and that in the same way in philosophy physical and logical research should be brought to bear on ethics by which





<pb n="181"/>

the character is bettered and yearns to acquire and also to make use of virtue.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="76"><p> This is how we have

learned to regard the story of Abraham. Literally his name was changed, actually he changed over from nature-study to ethical philosophy and abandoned the study of the world to find a new home in the knowledge of its Maker, and from this he gained piety, the most splendid of possessions.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="77"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="11"/> We will now deal with the case of Sarah his

wife. Her name Sarai (Σάρα) is changed to Sarah (Σάρρα) by the addition of one letter, rho. These are the names, now for the facts
<note n="5.181.a"> See App. p. 589.</note>
  indicated by them. Sarai means my sovereignty, Sarah sovereign.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="78"><p> The

former is a symbol of specific virtue, the latter of generic, and in the same measure as the genus is greater than the species is the second name greater than the former. The species is small and perishable, the genus is large and imperishable.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="79"><p> And the gifts

which God wills to bestow are great and immortal in exchange for small and perishable, and to give such is a work well suited to Him. Wisdom in the good man is a sovereignty vested in himself alone, and its possessor will not err if he says “The wisdom in me is my sovereignty.” But in the wisdom which is its archetype, the generic wisdom, we cease to have the sovereignty of the particular individual, but sovereignty its very self.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="80"><p> And therefore that specific

wisdom will perish with its possessor, while the other which like a seal gave it its shape, being free from all mortal element, will continue for ever imperishable. So too with the arts: the specific arts perish with their owners, the geometricians, the grammarians, the musicians: the generic arts remain imperishable.


<pb n="183"/>

Incidentally another lesson suggested at the same time is that every virtue is a queen and a sovereign and a ruler of the course of human life.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="81"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="12"/> We shall also find that the change of Jacob’s

name to Israel is much to the purpose. Why so? Because Jacob is the supplanter, and Israel he who sees God. It is the task of a supplanter in the practice of virtue to disturb and shake and upset the supports on which passion rests, and all the firmness and stability which they have. That is a work which cannot commonly be done without hard effort and the stains of the arena, but only when one maintains the contests of wisdom to the end, and drilled in the gymnastics of the soul wrestles with the thoughts which oppose and hold it fast in their grip. The task of him who sees God is not to leave the sacred arena uncrowned, but carry off the prizes of victory.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="82"><p> And

what garland more fitting for its purpose or of richer flowers could be woven for the victorious soul than the power which will enable him to behold the Existent with clear vision? Surely that is a glorious guerdon to offer to the athlete-soul, that it should be endowed with eyes to apprehend in bright light Him Who alone is worthy of our contemplation.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="83"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="13"/> It is worth inquiring why Abraham, after

the change of name, is not called by his old name, but always receives the same title as his right, whereas Jacob, after he is addressed as Israel, is in spite of this called Jacob many and many a time. We must reply that these are signs differing according as virtue acquired by teaching differs from virtue acquired by practice.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="84"><p> He who is improved through

teaching, being endowed with a happy nature, which with the co-operation of memory assures his retentiveness,

<pb n="185"/>

gets a tight grip and a firm armhold of what he has learned and thus remains constant. The Practiser on the other hand, after strenuous exercise, takes a breathing-space and a relaxation while he collects and recovers the force which has been enfeebled by his labours. In this he resembles the athletes who anoint their bodies. When they are weary with exercise they pour oil upon their limbs to prevent their forces being utterly shattered by the intensity and severity of the contest.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="85"><p> Again, the Man of Teaching has to aid him the voice

of his monitor ringing in his ears, deathless as that monitor himself, and thus never swerves: the Man of Practice has only his own will which he exercises and drills to aid him to overthrow the passion natural to created being, and, even if he reaches the consummation, yet through weariness he returns to his old kind.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="86"><p> He is more patient of toil, the other more blessed by

fortune. This last has another for his teacher, while the toiler, self-helped only, is busied in searching and inquiring and zealously exploring the secrets of nature, engaged in labour ceaseless and unremitting.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="87"><p> Therefore did Abraham in token of the even tenor

of his future life receive his new name from God, the unchangeable, that the stability of his future might be set on a firm foundation by Him Who stands and is ever the same in nature and condition. But Jacob was re-named by an angel, God’s minister, the Word, in acknowledgement that what is below the Existent cannot produce permanence unswerving and unwavering, but only such harmony as is found in a musical instrument wherein the tones now stretched to a

<pb n="187"/>

high pitch, now relaxed to a low, are blended into melody by the artist’s skill.
<note n="5.187.a">Literally “as in a musical instrument containing heightenings and lowerings of notes to the artistic blending of melody.”</note>


</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="88"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="14"/> Again, while the race has three founders it

is the first and last of these, Abraham and Jacob, whose names were changed, while the middle founder, Isaac, has the same name throughout. Why is this? Because both the scholar’s form of virtue and the practiser’s are open to improving influences, since the former desires to know what he is ignorant of, the latter desires crowns of victory and the prizes offered to a soul which rejoices to toil and seek the vision of the truth. On the other hand the kind which has no teacher or pupil but itself, being made what it is by nature rather than by diligence, goes on its way from the first equal and perfect like an even number
<note n="5.187.b">ἄρτιον here combines its ordinary sense of “perfect” or “complete” with its technical use for an “even” number.</note>
  with no other needed as complement.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="89"><p><milestone unit="para"/>Not so with the controller of bodily necessaries,

Joseph. For he changes his name and receives the title of Psonthomphanech
<note n="5.187.c">Hebrew and E.V. Zaphenath-paneah.</note>
  (Gen. xli. 45) from the king of the country. The meaning of this also needs explanation. Joseph is by interpretation “addition,” and conventional goods are an adjunct of natural goods. The former are such as gold, silver, chattels, revenues, services of menials, abundant stocks of heirlooms and furniture and all other luxuries, and the instruments of pleasure ready to hand in numberless forms.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="90"><p> The provider and superintendent of these,

Joseph, is found to have the appropriate name of “Addition,” since he is invested with the direction of the imported adventitious wealth which is an addition to the natural. This is attested by the



<pb n="189"/>

oracles which state that he stored up the food and managed the provisioning of the whole land (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>. 48) of the body.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="91"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="15"/> Such a character the

tokens given lead us to find in Joseph. Let us consider the nature of Psonthomphanech. His name means “mouth which judges in answer.” For every fool thinks that the man of wealth who lives surrounded by a sea of outward kinds of substance must of necessity be able to reason aright, be capable of answering questions put to him and capable of originating judgements of value. And in general the fool holds wisdom to be subordinate to chance, instead of chance to wisdom, as he should do, since the unstable ought to be guided on its course by the stable.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="92"><p> And also his uterine brother

is addressed by his father as Benjamin and by his mother as Son of sorrow, and that is true to facts. For Benjamin by interpretation is Son of days, and the day is illumined by the sunlight visible to our senses, to which we liken vainglory.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="93"><p> Such glory has

a certain brilliance to the outward sense, in the laudations bestowed by the vulgar multitude, in the decrees which are enacted, in the dedications of statues and images, in purple robes and golden crowns, in chariots and four-horse cars and crowded processions. He who affects these things was with good reason named the Son of days, that is of the visible light and of the brilliance of vainglory.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="94"><p> This name

which exactly expresses the fact is given him by his father the head of the house, the reason. But the soul gives him the one that agrees with the experience by which she herself has learned. She calls him a son of sorrow. Why? Because those

<pb n="191"/>

who are swept along by the current of empty opinion are thought to be happy, but are in reality most unhappy,
</p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="95"><p>
for many are the counterblasts, envy,

jealousies, continuous quarrelling, rancorous enmities unreconciled till death, feuds handed down successively to children’s children, an inheritance which cannot be possessed.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="96"><p> And so God’s interpreter

could not but represent the mother of vainglory as dying in the very pangs of childbirth. Rachel died, we read, in hard labour (Gen. xxxv. 16, 19), for the conception and birth of vainglory, the creature of sense, is in reality the death of the soul.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="97"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="16"/> Again, when the sons of Joseph, Ephraim

and Manasseh, were likened to the two elder sons of Jacob, Reuben and Simeon, have we not something perfectly true to nature?
<note n="5.191.a">As noted in the Introduction, §§ 97–102 are obviously irrelevant, as none of the four persons discussed have any change of name. The only link is that they show how different names symbolize contrasting qualities. Possibly the thought is partly induced by the proximity of the two sons of Rachel, <hi rend="italic">cf</hi>. the digression in <hi rend="italic">Quis Her</hi>. 252–266.</note>
  Jacob says, “Thy two sons who were born in Egypt before I came to Egypt are mine. Ephraim and Manasseh shall be as Reuben and Simeon to me” (Gen. xlviii. 5). Let us observe how the two pairs tally with each other.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="98"><p> Reuben, whose name is by interpretation “Seeing

son,” is the symbol of natural excellence, because the man who enjoys facility of apprehension and natural excellence is endowed with sight. Ephraim, as we have often said elsewhere,
<note n="5.191.b">See <hi rend="italic">Leg. All</hi>. iii. 91 f., <hi rend="italic">De Sobr</hi>. 27 f., <hi rend="italic">De Mig</hi>. 205 f., <hi rend="italic">De Cong</hi>. 40 f.</note>
  is the symbol of memory. For he is by interpretation “Fruit-bearing,” and memory is the best fruit of the soul. And no two things can be so close akin as memory and natural excellence.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="99"><p> Again, Simeon is another



<pb n="193"/>

name for learning and teaching, since Simeon is by interpretation “hearing,” and it is the peculiar mark of the learner that he hears and attends to what is said, while Manasseh is the symbol of recollection, for his name is “From forgetfulness.”
</p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="100"><p>
The advance

from forgetfulness necessarily involves recollection, and recollection is akin to learning. For what he has acquired often floats away from the learner’s mind, because in his weakness he is unable to retain it, and then emerges and starts again. When it flows away we say he is in a state of forgetfulness, and when it returns we call it a state of recollection.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="101"><p> Surely then memory closely corresponds to natural

excellence and recollection to learning. And the same relation which Simeon or learning bears to Reuben or nature is borne by Manasseh or recollection to Ephraim or memory.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="102"><p> For just as natural

excellence which resembles sight is better than learning which resembles hearing, the inferior of sight, so memory is in every way the superior of recollection, since while that is mixed with forgetfulness memory remains from first to last free from mixture or contamination.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="103"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="17"/> Again, the chief prophet’s father-in-law is

sometimes called in the oracles Jethro and sometimes Raguel. He is Jethro when vanity is flourishing, for Jethro is by interpretation “superfluous,” and vanity is to the verities of life a superfluity deriding as it does equalities and the mere necessaries of life and glorifying surplusage and inequality.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="104"><p>
<note n="5.193.a">Or “the inequalities produced by covetousness.”</note>
  Jethro values

the human above the divine, custom above laws, profane above sacred, mortal above immortal, and in general seeming above being. And he ventures


<pb n="195"/>

to come self-bidden and take the position of an adviser and suggests to the sage that he should not teach the only thing worth learning, the ordinances of God and the law, but the contracts which men make with each other, which as a rule produce dealings where the partners have no real partnership.
<note n="5.195.a">The suggestion of Mangey and Wendland to explain away this extraordinary perversion of the story of Jethro’s visit to Moses by transferring the negatives seems to me quite untenable. If it brings the passage into better agreement with the LXX, it does so at the cost of making nonsense of the whole, by representing something which is to Jethro’s credit as being to his discredit. Moreover, the text as it stands substantially agrees with the account of the interview given more shortly in <hi rend="italic">De Ebr.</hi> 37. Philo apparently gets his interpretation by stopping short at v. 17 of Ex. xviii. and ignoring the rest. Moses has said that he teaches the people “the ordinances of God and the law,” and Jethro replies οὐκ ὀρθῶς ποιεῖς. The sequel goes on to shew that Jethro means that Moses should employ subordinates for minor matters, and the last part of § 104 seems to be a vague reproduction of this, but completely twisted, whether through perversity or lapse of memory, so as to describe a policy of injustice called in <hi rend="italic">De Ebr.</hi> “playing the demagogue, and laying down laws contrary to the laws of nature.”</note>
  And the great ones
<note n="5.195.b"><hi rend="italic">Prima facie</hi> no doubt we should take ὁ μέγας as meaning Moses, particularly as Moses in the story does accept Jethro’s suggestion. But in view of the impossibility of Philo ascribing to Moses the acceptance of such advice, I take it generically, and this fits in with the evidently intended antithesis to μεγάλοις μεγάλα.</note>
  of the earth accept all he says, and think that it is right to give great justice to the great and little justice to the little.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="105"><p>
<note n="5.195.c">The Greek might mean “assigns important administrations of justice, etc.,” but here again the overwhelming argument of the necessity of discrediting Jethro demands the translation given. Philo is perhaps thinking of Deut. i. 17, and xxiv. 13–16, where the thought suggested in the translation appears.</note>
  Yet often this

wiseacre changes round and leaves the flock which had him in his blindness for their leader: he seeks the herd of God and becomes therein a member without reproach, so much does he admire the nature of its herdsman and reverence the skill in governing which he shews in the charge of his flock. For the meaning of Raguel (Ex. ii. 18) is “the shepherding of God.”

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="106"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="18"/> I have stated the sum

of the matter, Moses will shew us the proofs. In the first place he describes him as one who honours





<pb n="197"/>

judgement and justice. For the word Midian when translated appears as “from judgement or sifting.” This has a twofold significance.
<note n="5.197.a">i.e. ἐκ κρίσεως may be taken as a single word ἐκκρίσεως, or as “belonging to judgement,” though in ἐκ λήθης (§ 100) the ἐκ is supposed to indicate the opposite of the noun.</note>
  It means in one sense sifting out and sifting off, which we often see in the case of those who enter for the so-called sacred games.
<note n="5.197.b">See App. p. 589.</note>
  For thousands of these who have been judged to be unfit have been known to be sifted out by the stewards.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="107"><p> Midianites, in this sense, initiated

in the unholy rites of Baal Peor (Num. xxv. 3), and widening all the orifices of the body to receive the streams which pour in from outside (for the meaning of Baal Peor is “mouth of skin above
<note n="5.197.c">Or “mouth above skin” (or “leather,” cf. δερμάτινον ὄγκον Βεελφεγώρ, <hi rend="italic">De Conf.</hi> 55). I take the application to be that δέρμα indicates the body, and, if the form given in the translation is right, ἀνωτέρω suggests that in this case the body has usurped the superiority which belongs to the mind.</note>
 ”), flood the ruling mind and sink it to the lowest depths, so that it cannot float up to the top or rise ever so little.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="108"><p> And this was its condition until the Man of Peace,

an evident
<note n="5.197.d">A strange use of τρανός. No satisfactory emendation is suggested. Wend.’s τρανὸς &lt;λόγος&gt; is fairly satisfactory in itself, but the λόγον which follows is an objection.</note>
  priest of God, Phinehas (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>. 12, 13), came a self-bidden champion. He is a hater of evil by nature and possessed by zeal for the good.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="109"><p> And when he took the lance,
<note n="5.197.e">For σειρομάστην and other points in this sentence see the parallels, <hi rend="italic">Leg. All.</hi> iii. 242, <hi rend="italic">De Post</hi>. 183, <hi rend="italic">De Ebr</hi>. 73, and notes thereon.</note>
  that is the sharp-edged word, able to probe and explore each thing, power was granted him, that duped by none and armed with mighty strength he should pierce passion through the womb, that it should henceforth bring to birth no plague of God’s sending (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>. 7, 8). It is against

these Midianites that the nation of vision sets on foot the greatest of wars in which none of their




<pb n="199"/>

combatants was “lost”
<note n="5.199.a">See notes on <hi rend="italic">De Conf.</hi> 56 and <hi rend="italic">De Ebr.</hi> 144. Here there is no allusion to the original meaning of the word, and the derived sense of “is lost” may be given in the translation.</note>
  (Num. xxxi. 49), but returned safe and unwounded, crowned with the garlands of victory.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="110"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="19"/> The above is one of the


types indicated by the word Midian; another is the judicial, justice-dispensing type which by marriage is akin to the prophetic sort. “The priest” of judgement and justice, he says, “had seven daughters” (Ex. ii.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="111"><p> 16). The daughters stand as a symbol for

the seven faculties of the unreasoning element, namely reproductive power, speech, and the five senses. “Daughters,” it adds, “who kept the sheep of their father,” for through these seven faculties come the advances
<note n="5.199.b">προβάσεις evidently alludes to the idea that πρόβατον is derived from προβαίνω, <hi rend="italic">cf. De Sac.</hi> 112 προκοπῆς δὲ πρόβατον, ὡς καὶ αὐτὸ δηλοῖ τοὔνομα, σύμβολον.</note>
  and growths which repeated apprehension produces in the father, the mind. Each of these faculties “arrives at” its own, sight at colours and forms, hearing at sounds, smell at scents, taste at flavours, and the others at the objects appropriate to each in particular. Each “draws up,” so to speak, external objects of sense until they “fill the troughs” of the soul “from which they water the sheep of the father,” and by these I mean the purest of flocks, the flock of reasoning which brings with it at once protection and adornment.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="112"><p>
<note n="5.199.c">This is explained later in § 246.</note>
  But then “arrive” the comrades of envy and malice,

the shepherds of an evil herd, and drive them from the uses prescribed by nature (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>. 17). For whereas the daughters take outside objects inside to the mind, which is as it were their judge and king, hoping thus under the best of rulers to perform their duty aright,
</p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="113"><p>
 the others beset and pursue them and give the

opposite orders, namely that they should entice the



<pb n="201"/>

mind outside and there deliver over phenomena into its hand.
<note n="5.201.a">The thought is obscure. Cohn and Wend. proposed ἀγώγιμον παραδιδόναι τοῖς φαινομένοις (or πρὸς τὰ φαινόμενα). If the text is kept, I suggest that the thought may be that while the mind holds its proper seat, it makes the right use of αἰσθητά, but if it is enticed out into the body-loving region, αἰσθητά are used by it as slaves or prisoners. This would be brought out more clearly if we made the easy correction καὶ &lt;ἐκεῖ&gt; παραδιδόναι. But Mangey’s emendation of ποιμαινόμενα for φαινόμενα would greatly simplify the imagery and deserves all consideration. See App. pp. 589 f.</note>
  And in this way they will persist until the mind which loves virtue and is inspired by God, called Moses, shall “arise” from his former seeming quietude, protect and “save” the maidens from their subjugators, and nourish the flock of the father with words and thoughts, sweet as water to drink.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="114"><p> And

when the maidens have escaped the onset of those who are the mind’s enemies and have no aspiration but for the superfluities of life as though life were mere play-acting,
<note n="5.201.b">If this is right περίαπτα is used in a somewhat different sense from § 199 for “appendages”; cf. Aristot. <hi rend="italic">Nic. Eth.</hi> x. 8. 12 οὐδὲν δὴ προσδεῖται τῆς ήδονῆς ὁ βίος αὐτῶν, ὥσπερ περιάπτου τινός. For τραγῳδία <hi rend="italic">cf. De Post.</hi> 165 οἱ τραγῳδίαν τὸν βίον . . . νομίζοντες. But the words may refer to the masks of actors, and if so would be more in line with §§ 198, 199.</note>
  they return not now to Jethro but to Raguel. For they have discarded their kinship with vanity, and become affiliated to the guidance and rule of law,
<note n="5.201.c">See App. p. 590.</note>
  resolved to become a part of the holy herd which is led by God’s Word as its name shews, for Raguel means “the shepherding of God.”

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="115"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="20"/> And since God cares for His own flock He has

ready at hand a multitude of gifts for those of His charges who obey Him and do not rebel. In the Psalms there is a hymn of this kind, “The Lord is my shepherd, and nothing shall be lacking to me” (Ps. xxiii.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="116"><p> (xxii.) 1). So then we shall not be surprised

to find the mind which has the Divine Word for its shepherd and king asking of its seven daughters, “Why have ye returned with such speed and so eagerly to-day?” (Ex. ii. 18). For at other times when you visited the objects of sense you spent a




<pb n="203"/>

long time out there and almost refused to return, so greatly were you enticed by them. But now something or other has induced you to come back with this unwonted eagerness.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="117"><p> So they will reply that

this hasty breathless racing out to the world of sense and back again is not due to themselves but to the man who rescued them from the shepherds of the savage herd, and they call Moses an Egyptian (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> 19), Moses who was not only a Hebrew, but of that purest Hebrew blood which alone is consecrated. They cannot, that is, rise above their own nature.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="118"><p> For the senses are on the border-line between the

intelligible realm and the sensible, and all that we can hope is that they should desire both realms and not be led by the latter only. To suppose that they will ever give their affections to the things of mind only would be the height of folly, and therefore they give both titles. By the word “man” they point out the world which reason alone discerns,
<note n="5.203.a">For “Man” standing for the true man, the mind, <hi rend="italic">cf. De Agr</hi>. 9, <hi rend="italic">Quis Rerum</hi> 231, <hi rend="italic">De Fug.</hi> 71, and elsewhere.</note>
  by “Egyptian” they represent the world of sense.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="119"><p> On

hearing this the father will ask again, where is the man? (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>. 20). In what part of your surroundings does the element of the reason dwell? Why have you left him so easily, and why when you once fell in with him did you not take to your arms that treasure, so beautiful above all, so profitable to yourselves?</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="120"><p> But if you have not as yet, at least now “invite him

that he may eat” (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>. 20) and feed on your advance to higher stages of goodness and a closer affinity to him. Perhaps he will even dwell among you and wed the winged, inspired and prophetic nature called Zipporah (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>. 21).

<pb n="205"/>

<milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="21"/> So much for this.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="121"><p> But Moses also changes

the name of Hoshea to Joshua (Num. xiii. 17), thus transforming the individual who embodies a state into the state itself.
<note n="5.205.a">ποιός (a person of a particular kind) is regularly used in antithesis to other ποιοί or ἄποιοι; but it may also be used in antithesis to ποιότης, <hi rend="italic">cf</hi>., ποιόν τι ἀλλ᾿ οὐ ποιότητα, <hi rend="italic">Theaetetus</hi> 182 A. In this case the ποιός is the concrete of the abstract ποιότης. Philo has used it in exactly the same way in <hi rend="italic">Leg. All</hi>. i. 67, 79, and also in <hi rend="italic">Leg. All</hi>. ii. 18, where ὁ κατὰ τὰς ἀρετὰς ποιός is φρόνιμος or σώφρων, etc., corresponding to φρόνησις, σωφροσύνη, etc.</note>
  For Hoshea by interpretation is “he,” that is a particular individual, “is saved.” But Joshua is “safety of the Lord,” a name for the best possible state.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="122"><p> For states are better than the

individuals who embody them, as music is better than the musician and medicine than the physician, and every art than every artist, better both in everlastingness and in power and in unerring mastery over its subject matter. The state is everlasting, active, perfect; the individual is mortal, acted on, imperfect; and the imperishable is higher and greater than the mortal, the acting cause than that on which it acts, and the perfect than the imperfect.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="123"><p> Thus in the

above also we see the coin which represents the man re-minted in a better form. But in Caleb we have a total change of the man himself. For we read “there was another spirit in him” (Num. xiv. 24), as though the ruling mind in him was changed to supreme perfection.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="124"><p> For Caleb is by interpretation “all heart,” and this is a figurative way of shewing

that his was no partial change of a soul wavering and oscillating, but a change to proved excellence of the whole and entire soul which dislodged anything that


<pb n="207"/>

was not entirely laudable by thoughts of repentance; for when it thus washed away its defilements, and made use of the lustrations and purifications of wisdom, it could not but be clean and fair.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="125"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="22"/> The chief of the prophets proves to have

many names. When he interprets and teaches the oracles vouchsafed to him he is called Moses; when he prays and blesses the people, he is a Man of God (Deut. xxxiii. 1); and when Egypt is paying the penalties for its impious deeds he is the god (Ex. vii. 1) of Pharaoh, the king of the country.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="126"><p> Why

these three? Because to enact fresh laws for the benefit of those to whom they would apply is the task of one whose hands are ever in touch with divine things, one who is called up (Ex. xxiv. 1) by the Lawgiver who speaks in oracles, one who has received from Him a great gift, the power of language to express prophet-like the holy laws. For Moses, if translated, is a “receiving”
<note n="5.207.a">Or “a thing received,” the natural meaning of the word, i.e. Moses is named after the gift which he has received.</note>
  and it also means a handling, as shewn above.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="127"><p>
<note n="5.207.b">The meaning is obscure. Perhaps the fact that Moses “handled” the laws shews that his name of “receiving” must also be understood to include the kindred meaning of “handling.” The derivation here given applies only to the last part of the name. The common ancient derivation that “Mo” represented the Egyptian μῶυ, “water,” is given by Philo, <hi rend="italic">De Mos</hi>. i. 17, In <hi rend="italic">Leg. All.</hi> iii. 231 ψηλάφημα was used for “groping” (in darkness).</note>
  Secondly, to pray and bless

is not for any chance person but for a man who has had no eyes
<note n="5.207.c">Clearly an allusion to the blessing of Levi (Deut. xxxiii. 9), “who said to his father and mother ‘I have not seen thee’ (οὐχ ἑώρακα)” <hi rend="italic">Cf. De Fug.</hi> 89 and elsewhere. Mangey and Wend, needlessly suspect the word.</note>
  for his kinship to created being and has given himself to be the portion of Him who is ruler and father of all.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="128"><p> For one must be content if it be

granted to him to follow right reasoning himself, but to procure the good gift for others is what only a greater, more perfect, truly God-inspired soul can



<pb n="209"/>

promise, and the possessor of such a soul will with good reason be called God’s man.
<note n="5.209.a">Philo, as often, connects εὐλογιστία with εὐλογία. See note on <hi rend="italic">De Sobr.</hi> 18.</note>
  Thirdly, this same person is a god, because he is wise and therefore the ruler of every fool, even though that fool boast ever so loudly in the support of his royal sceptre. And he is a god for this reason in particular.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="129"><p> It is the will

of the ruler of all that though there be some doomed to punishment for their intolerable misdeeds, they should have mediators to make intercession for them, who imitating the merciful power of the Father will dispense punishment with more moderation and in a kindlier spirit. Beneficence is the peculiar prerogative of a god.
<note n="5.209.b">The thought is: Moses’ “godship” to Pharaoh was particularly shewn in his not punishing him summarily, but allowing him so many chances of repenting, and in interceding with God for him, e.g. Ex. ix. 29.</note>


</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="130"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="23"/> We have now dealt sufficiently with the

change and substitution of names and will proceed to the next points in our inquiry. What followed at once was the promise of the birth of Isaac. For after calling his mother Sarah instead of Sarai He says to Abraham, “I will give thee a child from her” (Gen. xvii. 16). Each part of this must be severally examined.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="131"><p> First, then, the giver of anything in the

proper sense of the word must necessarily give something which belongs to himself, and if this is so Isaac must be not the man Isaac but the Isaac whose name is that of the best of the good emotions, joy, the Isaac who is the laughter of the heart, a son of God,





<pb n="211"/>

who gives him as a means to soothe and cheer truly peaceful souls.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="132"><p> It were a monstrous thing that one

should be a husband, and another the parent, parent therefore of bastards born in adultery, and yet Moses writes of God as the husband of the virtue-loving mind when he says, “The Lord seeing that Leah was hated opened her womb” (Gen. xxix.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="133"><p> 31), for moved by pity and compassion for the virtue

hated by our mortal race and for the soul that loves virtue he sends barrenness (on the favourite and gives honour) to the nature which loves excellence and opens the fountain of happy parentage by granting her welfare in childbirth.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="134"><p> And Tamar


too; she bore within her womb the divine seed, but had not seen the sower.
<note n="5.211.a">For §§ 134–136 <hi rend="italic">cf. De Fug.</hi> 149 ff.</note>
  For we are told that at that hour she veiled her face (Gen. xxxviii. 15), just as Moses when he turned aside fearing to look upon God (Ex. iii. 6). But she closely scanned the symbols and tokens, and judging in her heart that these were the gifts of no mortal she cried aloud, “To whomsoever these belong, he it is by whom I am with child” (Gen. xxxviii. 25). <milestone unit="section" n="135"/>
Whose is the ring,

the pledge of faith, the seal of the universe, the archetypal idea by which all things without form or quality before were stamped and shaped? Whose is the cord, that is, the world-order, the chain of destiny,
<note n="5.211.b">See App. p. 590.</note>
  the correspondence and sequence of all things, with their ever-unbroken chain? Whose is the staff, that is the firmly planted, the unshaken, the unbending; the admonition, the chastening, the





<pb n="213"/>

discipline; the sceptre, the kingship! whose are they? Are they not God’s alone?</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="136"><p> And therefore the

temper which makes confession of thankfulness, that is Judah, pleased at the divine inspiration which masters her, says with all boldness, “She is justified since I gave her to no mortal” (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>. 26), for he holds it impiety to defile the divine with things profane.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="137"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="24"/> So, too, the wisdom which as in motherhood

brought forth the nature of the self-taught declares that God had begotten it. For when the child is born she says with pride, “The Lord has made laughter for me” (Gen. xxi. 6). That is the same as saying” He formed, He wrought, He begot, Isaac,” since Isaac and laughter are the same.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="138"><p> But this

saying is not for all to hear, so strongly does the evil tide of superstition flow in our minds and drown unmanly and degenerate souls.
<note n="5.213.a">See App. p. 590.</note>
  And therefore she adds” Whoever shall hear will rejoice with me” (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>) as though there were few whose ears are opened and pricked up to receive these holy words, which teach us that to sow and beget the excellent is the peculiar task of God alone. To this lesson all but those few are deaf.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="139"><p> I remember too an oracle given

by a prophet’s mouth in words of fire which runs thus: “From Me thy fruit has been found. Who is wise and he shall understand them, who is understanding and he shall know them?” (Hos. xiv. 9, 10).
<note n="5.213.b"><hi rend="italic">Cf. De Plant</hi>. 138.</note>
  Under the prophet’s words I recognized the voice of the invisible master whose invisible hand plays on the instrument of human speech, and I was lost in admiration at the saying also.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="140"><p> For all that is good

in the range of existing things or rather the whole heaven and universe is in very truth God’s fruit, the



<pb n="215"/>

inseparable growth, as it were, of the tree of His eternal and never-fading nature. And to know and confess such things is for the wise and understanding, not for men of no account.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="141"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="25"/> So much for the phrase “I will give to

thee.” We must now explain “from her.” Some understand by it that which comes into being outside her, thinking that in the judgement of right reason the best decision is that the soul should declare that nothing good belongs to herself, but all is an addition from outside, through the high benevolence of God Who showers His gifts of grace.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="142"><p> Others


take it as “immediate,” “with speed.” They say that ἐξ αὐτῆς is equivalent to “straightway,” “at once,” “without postponement,” “without delay,” and this is the way in which the gifts of God are wont to be given, outrunning even the moments of time. There is a third class who say that virtue is the mother of any good that has come into being, receiving the seeds of that being from nothing that is mortal.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="143"><p> Again, some ask whether the


barren can bear children, since the oracles earlier describe Sarah as barren and now admit that she will become a mother. Our answer to this must be that it is not in the nature of a barren woman to bear, any more than of the blind to see or of the deaf to hear. But as for the soul which is sterilized to wickedness and unfruitful of the endless host of passions and vices, scarce any prosper in childbirth as she. For she bears offspring worthy of love, even the number seven according to the hymn of Hannah, that is, grace, who says “The barren hath borne seven, but she that is much in children hath languished” (1 Sam. ii.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="144"><p> 5).



<pb n="217"/>
<milestone unit="para"/>She applies the word “much” to the mind which is a medley of mixed and confused thoughts, which, because of the multitude of riots and turmoils that surround it, brings forth evils past all remedy. But the word “barren” she applies to the mind which refuses to accept any mortal sowing as fruitful, the mind which makes away with and brings to abortion all the intimacies and the matings of the wicked, but holds fast to the “seventh”
<note n="5.217.a">For this use of ἑβδόμη for ἑβδομάς see note on § 260.</note>
  and the supreme peace which it gives. This peace she would fain bear in her womb and be called its mother.
</p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="145"><p>
<milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="26"/> Such is the meaning of “from her.” Let

us now examine the third part of the phrase used, namely “child.” First then we may well wonder why He does not say He will give many children, but will grant one only. Why? Because excellence cannot be estimated by number but rather by value.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="146"><p> For, to take examples at random, there are ever so

many musical, grammatical and geometrical things, and just and prudent and courageous and temperate things, but music and grammar and geometry in the abstract and again justice and temperance and prudence and courage in the abstract are each of them one thing, the original, the same as the archetypal idea, and from this origin the many and indeed infinite particulars
<note n="5.217.b">See App. p. 591.</note>
  have been formed.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="147"><p> So much for

His saying that He will give one, but the word actually used in this passage, “bairn,” is used not without care or consideration. He wishes to shew that the child is not alien or supposititious, nor again adopted or bastard, but the truly genuine and free-natured
<note n="5.217.c">For this play upon ἀστῆς and ἀστεῖον (for which Mangey needlessly wished to substitute ἀστὸν <hi rend="italic">cf. De Mig.</hi> 99 ἀσταί τε καὶ ἀστεῖαι γυναῖκες and note on <hi rend="italic">De Conf.</hi> 106.</note>


<pb n="219"/>

offspring of a free-born soul. For “bairn” derived from “bearing” is used to bring out the affinity which is the natural tie between parents and children.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="148"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="27"/> “I will bless her,” He continues, “and

she shall be for nations.” He shews hereby that not only is generic virtue divided into its proximate species and their subdivisions, as into nations, but also that actions and ideas have nations in a sense, just as living creatures have, and that to these nations the addition of virtue is most beneficial.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="149"><p> For everything

that lacks or has lost prudence is a source of mischief, just as all must be in darkness on which the sun does not shine. By virtue the husbandman takes better care of his plants; by virtue the charioteer guides his chariot in the horse-race without a fall; by virtue the helmsman steers his vessel safe through the voyage. Virtue again produces better conditions
in households, city and country, by producing men who are good household managers, statesmanlike and neighbourly.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="150"><p> Virtue, too, introduces the best laws,

and sows everywhere seeds of peace. And in proof of this we see that where the opposite condition prevails the natural result is the opposite of these blessings, namely war, lawlessness, misgovernment, confusion, disasters at sea, revolutions, and in the realm of the sciences that most painful disease knavery, which causes them to be called perversions of art,
<note n="5.219.a">See App. p. 591.</note>
  rather than arts. Virtue then will necessarily extend to nations, that is, large and comprehensive combinations both of living creatures and of actions and ideas, and will thus benefit those who receive her.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="151"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="28"/> Next we read “And kings of nations

shall be from her,” for those whom she conceives and


<pb n="221"/>

bears are all rulers, chosen not for a short time by the uncertainty of lot or by the votes of men for the most part hirelings, but rulers appointed for ever by Nature herself.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="152"><p> And this is no invention of mine,

but a statement made by the most holy oracles, wherein certain people appear as saying to Abraham “Thou art a King from God among us” (Gen. xxiii. 6). They did not consider his material resources, for what such were there in an emigrant, who was not even the inhabitant of a city but a wanderer over a wide and desolate and trackless land? Rather they perceived the kingship in his mind, and thus Moses confesses that the Sage alone is king.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="153"><p>
<note n="5.221.a">See App. p. 591.</note>
  For in truth the prudent man is ruler of

the imprudent, for he knows what he should and should not do, and the temperate of the intemperate, for he has studied carefully how to choose and how to avoid: the brave man of the coward because he has learned with certainty what he should and should not endure: the just of the unjust, because he aims at unbiased equality in what he has to award:
<note n="5.221.a">See App. p. 591.</note>
  the holy of the unholy because high and true conceptions of God prevail with him.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="154"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="29"/> These promises might well have puffed up

the mind to soar into the heights. But to convict us, so often proud-necked at the smallest cause, he falls down and straightway laughs (Gen. xvii. 17) with the laughter of the soul, mournfulness in his face, but smiles in his mind, where joy vast and unalloyed has made its lodging.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="155"><p> For the sage who receives an

inheritance of good beyond his hope these two things are simultaneous—to fall and to laugh. He falls as a pledge that the proved nothingness of mortality


<pb n="223"/>

keeps him from vaunting: he laughs to shew that the thought that God alone is the cause of good and gracious gifts makes strong his piety.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="156"><p> Let created

being fall with mourning in its face; it is only what nature demands, so feeble in footing is it, so sad of heart in itself. Then let it be raised up by God and laugh, for God alone is its support and its joy.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="157"><p><milestone unit="para"/>One might reasonably question how it is possible

for anyone to laugh, when laughter had not yet come into being among us. For Isaac is laughter, which according to the view before us is not yet born. For as we cannot see without eyes nor hear without ears, nor smell without nostrils nor use the other senses without the corresponding organs, nor apprehend without the power of thought, so the act of laughing would be against all probability if laughter had not yet been created. What shall we say then?</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="158"><p> Nature

often provides signs which shew us beforehand future happenings. Do you not often see how the fledgling, before it actually oars its way in the air, likes to flutter or shake its wings, thus giving a welcome promise of ability to fly hereafter?</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="159"><p> Or how the lamb or the he-goat


or the youngling ox, if one provoke it, fronts its opponent and starts to defend itself with those parts from which spring the weapons of defence which Nature provides?</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="160"><p> Again, in the arena the bulls do

not at once gore their antagonists, but set their legs well apart, bend their necks slightly, and turn them either way with a truly bull-like glare, and only then do they attack and shew a mind to set to in earnest. This kind of thing, one impulse, that is, preluding




<pb n="225"/>

another, is called <hi rend="italic">orousis</hi>,
<note n="5.225.a">See App. p. 591.</note>
  or “springing,’’ by those who practise word-coining.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="161"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="30"/> Much the same

often befalls the soul. When good is hoped for, it rejoices in anticipation, and thus may be said to feel joy before joy, gladness before gladness. We may find in this a likeness to what happens in the vegetable world. They too, when they are going to bear fruit, put forth shoots, flowers and leaves in anticipation.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="162"><p> Observe the cultivated vine, what a wonderful piece

of nature’s handiwork it is, with its twigs, tendrils, suckers, petals, leaves, which seem almost to break out into speech and proclaim their joy at the coming fruit of the tree. And the day laughs in forecast while the dawning is still young because the sunrise is coming. For beam heralds beam and the dimmer light leads the way for the clearer.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="163"><p> And so the good

when it has come is accompanied by joy, and when it is expected, by hope. For we rejoice at its arrival and hope when it is coming. Similarly with their opposites. The presence of evil produces grief, and its expectation fear. And so fear is grief before grief, just as hope is joy before joy. For fear, I think, bears the same relation to grief as hope does to joy.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="164"><p> The senses, too, carry with them clear signs of what

is here stated. Smell presides over taste and passes judgement in advance on practically all that serves for food or drink. And therefore some looking to the obvious fact have given to smell the apposite name of fore-taster. And so it is natural for hope to taste beforehand as it were the coming good and to recommend




<pb n="227"/>

it to the soul which will have it for its solid possession.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="165"><p> Again the hungry or thirsty traveller, if

he suddenly sees in his journeying springs of water or trees of every kind laden with refreshing fruits, finds a preliminary satisfaction in the hope of future enjoyment, before he eats or drinks and even before he draws the water or plucks the fruit. And if we can find a feast in what feeds the body before we actually eat, can we possibly suppose that what feeds the mind is unable to give us a foretaste of gladness when the feast it provides is still to come?

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="166"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="31"/> Well then might he laugh even though

laughter seems to have been as yet unborn in our mortal race, and not only did he himself laugh but his wife also. For again we find Sarah laughed, saying in herself, “Not yet has this befallen me till now,” this unstudied, self-sprung good. Yet He that promised, she says, is “my Lord” (Gen. xviii. 12) and “older” than all creation, and I needs must believe Him.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="167"><p>
<note n="5.227.a">This perversion of the laughter of Abraham and Sarah has some excuse in the case of the latter in the obscurity of the LXX in which the E.V. “After I am waxed old shall I have pleasure, my lord being old also?” appears as here quoted. So also in <hi rend="italic">Leg. All.</hi> iii. 217 f.</note>
  At

the same time Moses teaches us this lesson that virtue is by its very nature a thing for joy,
<note n="5.227.b">See App. p. 591.</note>
  and that he who possesses it ever rejoices, while vice on the contrary is grievous and its possessor most unhappy.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="168"><p> After this need we extol those philosophers who declare that virtue is a state of happy feeling
<note n="5.227.c">Or “well-being.” See App. p. 591.</note>
 ? For,

see, we find in Moses the primary authority for this wise doctrine, since he pictures the good man as rejoicing and laughing, and elsewhere not the good man only but those also who come into company with him. “Seeing thee,” he says, “he will rejoice at it” (Ex. iv. 14).
<note n="5.227.d">See note on <hi rend="italic">De Mig.</hi> 79.</note>
  He suggests that the mere sight




<pb n="229"/>

of the worthy is enough to make the mind cast off the soul’s most hateful burden, grief, and to fill it with joy.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="169"><p> And to none of the wicked is rejoicing

permitted, as indeed the orations of the prophets proclaim: “Rejoicing is not for the impious, said God” (Is. xlviii. 22). It is indeed a divine saying and oracle that the life of every worthless man is one of gloom and sorrow and full of misery, even though he affect to wear a smiling face.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="170"><p> I would


not say that the Egyptians really rejoiced when they heard that Joseph’s brethren had come. Rather they assumed in hypocrisy the appearance of joy. For no fool when confronted by conviction is pleased with it, any more than the dissolute man on his sick-bed with the physician. For the profitable is followed by toil, the noxious by ease. And fools because they prefer ease to toil are naturally at enmity with those who would advise them to their profit.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="171"><p> And so when

you hear that “Pharaoh rejoiced and his servants” (Gen. xlv. 16) at the coming of the brothers of Joseph, do not suppose that they were really pleased, except perhaps at one thought: they expected once more to lead away the mind to desert its foster-brethren the goods of the soul for the numberless lusts of the body, and to debase its old ancestral coinage, the coinage of virtue its birth-fellow.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="172"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="32"/> With such

hopes the pleasure-loving mind is not content merely



<pb n="231"/>

to angle with the baits of every lust for the younger sort, the novices in the training-schools of temperance, but revolts from the idea that it should be unable to subjugate the older thinking, in which the frenzy of passion has passed its prime.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="173"><p>
<note n="5.231.a">i.e. at present only the brethren representing virtue at its earliest stages have come to Egypt. Egypt hopes also to win over the more perfected virtue of Jacob.</note>
  He makes other

offers, offers which mean loss though he speaks of them as profit. “Take your father and your wealth,” he says, “and come to me” (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> 18) into Egypt, come, that is, to this King of terror, who when our paternal and our truly real wealth had in virtue of its natural liberty left the body behind in its advance, draws it back and throws it with violence into a prison of exceeding bitterness; and over this prison he sets for keeper, as the oracular text tells us, Potiphar (Gen. xxxix. 1) the eunuch and chief cook
<note n="5.231.b">So LXX. E.V. “an officer of Pharaoh’s, the captain of the guard”; <hi rend="italic">cf. Leg. All.</hi> iii. 236.</note>
 : eunuch, because he has scant store of excellence and has lost by mutilation the soul’s organs of generation, unable further to sow and beget anything that tends to discipline; cook, because in cook-like fashion he slaughters living beings, chops and divides them, piece by piece, limb by limb, and moves in a chaos of lifeless carcasses, immaterial rather than material;
<note n="5.231.c">See note on <hi rend="italic">Quis Rerum</hi> 242.</note>
  and with his elaborately seasoned dishes arouses and excites the appetites of fruitless passions, appetites which should rather be tamed and calmed.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="174"><p> And also,

says the Pleasure-lover, “I will give you of all the good things of Egypt, and ye shall eat the marrow of the land” (Gen. xlv. 18). But we will answer him,” We do not accept the body’s good, for we have seen the things of the soul. For so deeply has our strong



<pb n="233"/>

yearning for these sunk into us that it can make us forget all that is dear to the flesh.”

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="175"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="33"/> Such indeed is the joy falsely so-called

of the fool. The true joy has been described above, the joy which befits the virtuous alone. “And so Abraham fell and laughed” (Gen. xvii. 17). He fell not from God but from himself, for in clinging to the immovable Being he stood, but fell from his own conceit.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="176"><p> And so when the spirit which is wise in its

own conceits had been thrown to the ground and the spirit of love to God raised up and firmly planted round Him who alone never bends, he laughed at once and said in his mind, “Shall this happen to one of a hundred years old, and shall Sarah being ninety years old bear a son?”
</p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="177"><p>
But do not think,


good reader, that when “he said” is followed by “in his mind” instead of “with his mouth,” the addition has little meaning. No, it is made with very careful purpose. Why so? Because in saying “Shall this happen to one of a hundred years,” he seems to doubt the birth of Isaac in which in an earlier place he was said to believe, as was shown by the oracular words delivered a little time before. Those ran, “He shall not be thine heir, but one who shall come from thee,” and then immediately followed the words, “And Abraham believed God and it was accounted to him for righteousness” (Gen. xv.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="178"><p> 4, 6). So then, since doubt was not consistent with

his past belief, Moses has represented the doubt not as long-lived, or prolonged to reach the mouth and tongue, but staying where it was with the swiftly moving mind. For, says the text, “He said in his mind,” which none of the creatures whose swiftness of foot we admire can outrun, and indeed no form

<pb n="235"/>

of bird nature has such speed.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="179"><p> This is, I think, the

reason why the poet most highly esteemed among the Greeks says, “like a bird’s wing or a thought.”
<note n="5.235.a"><hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> vii. 36, cf. the saying of Thales (Diog. Laert. i. 35) τάχιστον νοῦς· διά παντὸς γὰρ τρέχει.</note>
  He is showing the swiftness of the mind’s intensity, and to bring this out more strongly he puts thought after the bird’s wing. For the mind moves at the same moment to many things material and immaterial with indescribable rapidity and reaches at once the boundaries of land and sea, covering and dividing
<note n="5.235.b">The sense of the word is not clear. Wend, suggests συντέμνουσα “cutting down,” “making a short cut of.”</note>
  distances of infinite magnitude. At the same time it leaps so high from the earth that it passes through the lower to the upper air and scarcely comes to a stop even when it reaches the furthermost sphere of the fixed stars.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="180"><p> For its fiery fervent nature forbids

it to rest and its onward journey carries it across wide spaces outside the limits of all this world of sense to the world framed from the ideas to which it feels itself akin. So then in the case of the virtuous man the swerving was short, instantaneous and infinitesimal, not belonging to sense but only to mind, and so to speak timeless.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="181"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="34"/> But


perhaps it may be said, why did he, when once he had believed, admit any trace or shadow or breath of unbelief whatsoever? It seems to me that this question amounts to a wish to make out the created to be uncreated, the mortal immortal, the perishable imperishable, and if it is not blasphemy to say it, man to be God.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="182"><p> Such a person asserts that the faith

which man possesses should be so strong as to differ not at all from the faith which belongs to the Existent, a faith sound and complete in every way. For Moses



<pb n="237"/>

says in the Greater Song,
<note n="5.237.a">The common title for Deut. xxxii. in contrast to the song of Ex. xv.</note>
  “God is faithful and there is no injustice in Him” (Deut. xxxii.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="183"><p> 4), and it argues

great ignorance to think that the soul of man can contain the unwavering, absolutely steadfast excellences of God. Enough for man is the power to possess the images of these, images in the scale of number and magnitude far below the archetypes.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="184"><p> And surely this is to be expected, for the excellences

of God must needs be unmixed since God is not compounded but a single nature, whereas man’s excellences are mixed, since we, too, are mixtures, with human and divine blended in us and formed into a harmony in the proportions of perfect music, and a compound of more than one ingredient is subject to natural counter-forces drawing it to each of these ingredients.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="185"><p> Happy is he to whom it is

granted to incline towards the better and more godlike part through most of his life. For it is impossible that it should be so with him throughout the whole length of life; since sometimes the opposing load of mortality throws its weight into the scales, and biding its time waits to find its chance in the mischances of reason and so prove too strong for him.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="186"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="35"/> “Abraham then has believed God,” but only

as a man, so that you may recognize the weakness, the distinctive mark of the mortal, and learn that, if he swerves, his swerving arises only according to nature. But if that swerving is short and momentary, thanks are due, for many others have been overwhelmed by the rushing of the tide and died a violent death in the waters.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="187"><p> For, good friend, if you believe

the holy Moses, virtue is not sound-footed in our mortal and bodily nature, but limps ever so little and is subject to a sort of stiffness, for we are told that

<pb n="239"/>

“the width of the thigh was stiffened, and he halted on it” (Gen. xxxii. 25, 31).
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="188"><p><milestone unit="para"/>But perhaps some more courageous spirits might

come forward and say that the utterance does not even indicate any disbelief, but a prayer, that if joy, the best of good emotions, is to be born, its birth should be confined to the numbers ninety and a hundred, that so the perfect good may enter on its existence under perfect numbers.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="189"><p> The numbers here

named are perfect numbers, particularly according to the sacred writings. Let us consider each of them separately. To begin with Shem, the son of the just Noah, the ancestor of the nation of vision; he is said to have been a hundred years old when he begat Arphaxad (Gen. xi. 10), the meaning of whose name is “he disturbed affliction.” And surely it is excellent that the soul’s offspring should harass and confound and destroy injustice, afflicted and full of evils as it is.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="190"><p> Abraham too “plants

an acre”
<note n="5.239.a">i.e. Philo interprets ἄρουραν in the technical sense of a piece of land of 100 square cubits, cf. ἡ δὲ ἄρουρα ἐκατὸν πηχέων ἐστὶ Αἰγυπτίων πάντῃ, Herodotus ii. 168, <hi rend="italic">cf. De Plant.</hi> 75.</note>
  and adopts the hundred in measuring out the plot (Gen. xxi. 33), and Isaac “finds barley a hundredfold” (Gen. xxvi. 12); and Moses in building the court of the tabernacle takes a hundred cubits in measuring out the distance from east to west (Ex. xxvii.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="191"><p> 9). And a hundred too appears

in the firstfruit of firstfruit which the Levites offer to the consecrated priest (Num. xviii. 28), for when they receive the tenths from the nation, they are bidden to treat them as their own possessions and to give to the priest what may be called a holy tenth


<pb n="241"/>

of tenths.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="192"><p> And by observation we might discover

contained in the laws many other examples in praise of the number here mentioned, but the above is quite sufficient for the present. But if you
separate from the hundred a tenth as the sacred first offering to God who brings the fruits of the soul to their beginning,
<note n="5.241.a">For this use of φέρω see note on <hi rend="italic">Quis Rerum</hi> 36. So also in § 256 below. In § 225 the use is somewhat different, as there φέρειν precedes τίκτειν.</note>
  their increase and their fulfilment, you will leave behind another perfect number, ninety, for it must needs be perfect, placed as it is in a debatable land between the first and the tenth ten, and thus serve to separate sanctities from sanctities like the veil in the midst of the tabernacle (Ex. xxvi. 33), by which things of the same genus are distinguished through division into their respective species.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="193"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="36"/> The virtuous man then spoke truly virtuous


words and “with his mind.”
<note n="5.241.b">i.e. ἐν τῇ διανοίᾳ αὐτοῦ must under this second interpretation be understood not, as in the first interpretation, as indicating a passing thought, but as “sincerely.” Though Philo does not state this expressly, it is implied by the antithesis with κατὰ τὴν διάνοιαν τῆς παρθένου below.</note>
  But the wicked man sometimes gives admirable expression to noble thoughts, but his actions are most vile and their method equally so. Such a one is Shechem, the son of folly, for his father is Hamor whose name is translated by “ass,” while his own is interpreted as “shoulder,” the symbol of toil. The toil which is fathered by unintelligence is miserable and full of affliction, just as that which has intelligence for its





<pb n="243"/>

congener is profitable.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="194"><p> Thus the oracles say that

Shechem spake “according to the mind of the virgin” after first humiliating her (Gen. xxxiv. 2, 3). Are not these words” according to the mind of the virgin” added with exact thought so as almost to shew that his actions were the opposite of his words? For Dinah is incorruptible judgement, the justice which is the assessor of God, the ever virgin, for the word “Dinah” by interpretation is either judgement or justice.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="195"><p> The fools who attempt to seduce her by

their plottings and their practices repeated day by day seek by means of specious talking to escape from conviction. Now they should either make their actions conform to their words or if they persist in iniquity keep still. For by keeping still men say evil is halved. And so Moses by rebuking him who adjudges the chief honours to creation and only the second to the imperishable God says, “Thou hast sinned, be still” (Gen. iv.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="196"><p> 7).
<note n="5.243.a">For Philo’s use of this text see note on <hi rend="italic">De Sobr.</hi> 50.</note>
  For to rant and boast

of evil doings is a double sin. But what regularly happens with the multitude is this: they are ever addressing words of friendship and fairness to the maiden Virtue, but they let no occasion slip without using it to outrage and maltreat her if they can. What city is not crowded with those who hymn virtue the ever virgin?</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="197"><p> They tear to pieces the ears of all

they meet with such disquisitions as these, prudence is necessary, imprudence is harmful, temperance deserves our choice, intemperance our hatred; courage is worthy of perseverance
<note n="5.243.b">See App. pp. 591 f.</note>
  thesein, cowardice of avoidance; justice is profitable, injustice unprofitable; holiness is honourable, unholiness disgraceful;



<pb n="245"/>

piety is praiseworthy, impiety blameworthy; right purposing, speaking and acting is most conformable to man’s nature, wrong purposing, speaking and acting most alien to the same.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="198"><p> With a perpetual string

of this or suchlike talk they deceive the law-courts, the theatres, the council-chambers and every gathering and group of men, like people who set handsome masks on the ugliest of faces to prevent the ugliness being detected by the eyes of others.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="199"><p> But it is

all useless. The vindicators will come strong and doughty, inspired with zeal for virtue. They will strip off all this complication of wraps and bandages which the perverted art of the talkers has put together, and beholding the soul naked in her very self they will know the secrets hidden from sight in the recesses of her nature; and then exposing to every eye in clear sunlight her shame and all her disgraces they will point the contrast between her real character, so hideous, so despicable, and the spurious comeliness which disguised in her wrappings she counterfeited.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="200"><p> And the champions who stand ready

to repel such profane and impure ways of thinking are two in number, Simeon and Levi, but they are one in will. That is why in the blessings, while their father ranked them under a single head (Gen. xlix. 5), because their minds are in concord and harmony and their purpose set in one and the same direction, Moses ceases even to mention the pair, but compresses the whole of Simeon into Levi (Deut. xxxiii.




<pb n="247"/>

8), and thus blending the two natures he makes them one, bearing the stamp of a single form, and unites hearing with action.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="201"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="37"/> So when he understood the promise and

spoke “according to his mind” these words, so full of reverence and pious awe, the man of worth was moved by a twofold feeling, faith towards God, distrust of the creature. It is natural then that he should pray in these words, “Let this Ishmael live before thee” (Gen. xvii. 18), and each of the phrases here included, namely, “this,” “live,” “before Thee,” are applied by him appropriately. I say appropriately because many are deceived by the application of the same terms to denote different things. What I mean by this should be considered.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="202"><p>

Ishmael by interpretation is “hearing God,” but the divine truths are heard by some to their profit, by some to the harm of themselves and others.
Observe that dealer in augury, Balaam. He is described as “hearing the oracles of God and knowing knowledge from the Most High” (Num. xxiv.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="203"><p> 16), but what did he profit from such hearing

or such knowledge, he who attempted to bring ruin on the soul’s best eye which alone has been trained to see God? But yet what he willed he could not, so strong was the Saviour’s invincible might. Therefore, stabbed by his own madness, he received many wounds and perished” in the midst of the wounded” (Num. xxxi. 8) because with his soothsayer’s mock wisdom he defaced the stamp of heaven-sent prophecy.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="204"><p> Rightly then it is “this Ishmael” for whose

health alone the man of virtue prays, because of




<pb n="249"/>

those others who do not hear with honest mind the holy instructions, whom Moses absolutely forbade to resort to the assembly of the Ruler of all.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="205"><p> Such as in their pride extol their own mind and senses as the sole causes of all that happens amongst men—these are they who have spiritually lost the organs

of generation by crushing or complete mutilation; such again as love the creed which holds that gods are many and pays all honour to that fellowship of deities—these are the children of the harlot who knows not the one husband and father of the virtue-loving soul,—are not all such with good reason expelled and banished? (Deut. xxiii. 1, 2).
<note n="5.249.a"><hi rend="italic">Cf. De Mig.</hi> 69.</note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="206"><p>The parents too who accuse their son of wine-bibbing

seem to make a like use of the pronoun. They say “This son of ours is disobedient” (Deut. xxi. 20), and thus by the addition of “this” they shew that they have other sons, strong-willed and self-controlling, who obey the injunctions of right reason and instruction. For these two are the soul’s parents who can never lie, and to be accused by them is the greatest disgrace, as their praise is the highest glory.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="207"><p>
<note n="5.249.b">For the full development of this theme see <hi rend="italic">De Ebr.</hi> 13–94.</note>
  To take another instance, “It is this Moses and

Aaron whom God bade lead the sons of Israel from Egypt” (Ex. vi. 26), or “These are they who talked with Pharaoh the king” (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>. 27). In neither of these cases must we suppose that the words are used carelessly and that the demonstrative pronouns served no other purpose than to indicate
<note n="5.249.c">See App. p. 592.</note>
  the names.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="208"><p> For since Moses is mind at its purest, and Aaron is

its word, and each have been trained to holy things, the mind to grasp them as a God should and the word to express them worthily, the professors of


<pb n="251"/>

false wisdom mimic and debase this authentic coin, and say that what they think of the most excellent is just, and what they say of it worthy of praise (Ex. vii. 11). And so that when the spurious is set beside the authentic we may not be deceived by the likeness of the stamp he has given us a touchstone by which they may be distinguished.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="209"><p> What is this

touchstone? It is that he brought out of the land of the body the mind which could see and which loved wisdom and the vision. For he who could do this is “This Moses,” and he who could not, who had but the name and clothed himself with a multitude of grand-sounding titles, is made a laughing-stock.
<milestone unit="para"/>When he prays that Ishmael may live, he is not concerned with the life of the body, but prays that what he hears from God may abide for ever with the soul and stir him into living flame;

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="210"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="38"/> and

while Abraham prays, as we have said, that the grace of hearkening to holy words and learning holy truths may live, Jacob, the Man of Practice, prays for the life of natural goodness, for he says “Let Reuben live and not die” (Deut. xxxiii. 6).
<note n="5.251.a">Ascribed by inadvertence to the Blessing of Jacob, instead of to that of Moses.</note>
  Is he here praying that he should never know death and corruption, a gift impossible for a man? Surely not. Let us say then what he wishes to shew us.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="211"><p>

All that is heard or learned is a superstructure, built on the foundation of a nature receptive of instruction, for if nature be not there to begin with all else is useless. For those who are ungifted by nature would seem to differ not at all from an oak or mute stone, for nothing can adhere or fit into them, but all is shaken off and rebounds as from a solid substance.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="212"><p> But in the souls of the naturally



<pb n="253"/>

good we see a duly-tempered mixture like smooth wax, neither too solid nor too soft; a mixture which easily receives all that is seen and heard and itself reproduces perfectly the forms impressed upon it in lifelike copies preserved by memory.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="213"><p>
<note n="5.253.a"><hi rend="italic">Cf. Quis Rerum</hi> 181 where the simile is definitely referred to Plato (<hi rend="italic">Theaetetus</hi> 191 C).</note>
  Thus he was

bound to pray that the nation of reason should possess natural goodness free from disease and death. For the life of virtue, which is life in its truest form, is shared by few, and these few are not found among the vulgar herd, none of whom has part or lot in true life, but are only those to whom it is granted to escape the aims which engross humanity and to live to God alone.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="214"><p> And therefore the Man


of Practice and Courage wondered exceedingly that one who was borne along in the midstream of human life is not swept down by any rush of the swirling waters, but can breast the strong current of riches and stem the tide of pleasure’s ceaseless urge and keep his feet against the hurricane of vainglory.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="215"><p> And so Jacob says to Joseph, though indeed it is

rather the holy Word speaking to every man who in addition to bodily welfare is placed amidst abundance of the gear which makes for luxury, yet is proof against it all, “For thou still livest” (Gen. xlvi. 30). A marvellous utterance, which has travelled beyond the range of the common life which we lead, we who if we but catch a puff of the air of prosperity loosen every reef and let the breeze blow fresh and clear, and then with our strong steady wind to swell our canvas speed on to the enjoyments of the passions, and never do we draw in the loose and slack licence


<pb n="255"/>

of our lusts until we strike the rocks and wreck the whole bark of the soul.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="216"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="39"/> We
<note n="5.255.a">The objection of Cohn and Wendland to the first person ignores the fact that Philo constantly regards the stories and sayings of the Pentateuch as representing the spiritual experiences of every generation. It is “the holy word speaking to everyone,” as just above in § 215. Compare νοῦς ἡμῶν in § 16. Good examples appear in <hi rend="italic">De Som</hi>. i. 143 and 226, ii. 170. Cohn’s εὐχώμεθα does not fit in well with Philo’s use of παγκάλως (see note on <hi rend="italic">De Mig.</hi> 101). There would be no objection to εὐξόμεθα, but the change seems unnecessary.</note>
  do well indeed then when we pray

that this Ishmael may live. And so he adds “before God,” holding that in this lies the crown of happiness—that the mind should be privileged to live under the survey and watchful care of the Supreme Excellence.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="217"><p> For when the tutor is present his charge
<note n="5.255.b">See App. p. 592.</note>


will not go amiss; the teacher at the learner’s side brings profit to him; the company of his senior gives to the youth the grace of modesty and self-control; the mere sight of father or mother can silently prevent the son from some intended wrongdoing. Imagine then the vastness of the blessings which we must suppose will be his who believes that the eye of God is ever upon him, for if he reverences the dignity of Him who is ever present, he will in fear and trembling fly from wrongdoing with all his might.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="218"><p><milestone unit="para"/>But when he prays that Ishmael may live he does

not despair of the birth of Isaac, as I have said before, but while he has trusted in God &lt;he recognizes the weakness of humanity&gt;, for the gifts which God can give are not all such as man in his turn can receive, since for Him it is easy to bestow gifts, ever so many, ever so great, but for us it is no light matter to receive the proffered boons.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="219"><p> For it is enough for



<pb n="257"/>

us to obtain the good fruits of toil and effort, those more familiar gifts which grow up with us, but such as spring up independently without art or any form of human devising, which come ready-made to the recipient, we cannot even hope to attain. These are gifts of God, and therefore to discover them is the inevitable destiny of natures closer to God and undefiled and released from the mortal body.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="220"><p> Yet

Moses taught us to make our acknowledgements of thanks according to the power of our hands (Num. vi. 21), the man of sagacity dedicating his good sense and prudence, the master of words consecrating all the excellences of speech in praises to the Existent in poem or prose, and from others offerings after their kind, natural philosophy, ethical philosophy, the lore of the arts and sciences from the several students of the same.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="221"><p> In this way the sailor

will dedicate success of voyage, the husbandman fruitfulness of crops, the herdsman the teeming increase of his livestock, the physician the health of his patients, or again the general his victory in war, the statesman or crowned head his lawful preeminence or sovereignty, and in short he who is not self-centred will avow as the cause of all goods of the soul or body or outside the body Him who in very truth is the one sole Cause of aught.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="222"><p> Let none

then of the lowly or obscure in repute shrink through despair of the higher hope from thankful supplication to God, but even if he no longer expects any greater boon, give thanks according to his power for the gifts which he has already received.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="223"><p> Vast is the number

of such gifts, birth, life, nurture, soul, sense-perception, mental picturing, impulse, reasoning. Now
“reasoning” as a name is but a little word, but as

<pb n="259"/>

a fact it is something most perfect and most divine, a piece torn off from the soul of the universe, or, as it might be put more reverently
<note n="5.259.a">Philo again shews his doubt of the propriety of the phrase ἡ τοῦ παντὸς ψυχή, <hi rend="italic">cf. De Mig.</hi> 179 and note on <hi rend="italic">Leg.</hi> <hi rend="italic">All.</hi> i. 91.</note>
  following the philosophy of Moses, a faithful impress of the divine image.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="224"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="40"/> Well may we commend those members

of the scouting party who tried to pluck up by the roots the trunk of virtue and carry it away, and when they could not, took at least a branch and a single cluster, which was all they could carry (Num. xiii. 24), as a specimen and part of the whole.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="225"><p> We should

indeed pray that our course may lie amid the collected body of the many virtues. But if this be too great for human nature, let us be content whenever it be granted to consort with one of the specific virtues, with temperance, or courage, or justice or humanity. Let the soul carry in its womb and bring to the birth one good thing at least and not be unfruitful and barren of them all.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="226"><p> Would

you lay upon your own son such injunctions as these? If you do not treat your servants kindly, neither must you have neighbourly dealings with your equals. If you do not behave well to your wife, you must not honour your parents either. If you despise your father and mother, you must also shew impiety towards God. If you delight in pleasure, you must not refrain from covetousness. Do you covet great riches? Then also give way to vain conceit.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="227"><p> What,

I would ask, do you mean that it is wrong to use self-control in some things if you cannot do so in all? The son would surely reply, What do you mean, father? Would you have your son become either completely bad or completely good, and will you not


<pb n="261"/>

be satisfied if he chooses the midway course in preference to the extremes?</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="228"><p> It was


such a feeling that made Abraham, in the case of the destruction of Sodom, begin with fifty and end with ten (Gen. xviii. 24 f.) when he besought and supplicated that if the means of complete release to liberty (Lev. xxv. 10), which is symbolized by fifty, be not forthcoming in created beings, the lower training, which is numerically reckoned as ten, may be accepted to respite the soul which stands on the verge of condemnation.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="229"><p>
<note n="5.261.a"><hi rend="italic">Cf. De Sac.</hi> 122.</note>
  The trained have the

advantage over the untrained, and those who are familiar with the culture of the schools over minds untuned to the muse; they start with better opportunities for growth, because as a rule from boyhood they have been bathed in a stream of ideas which deal with endurance and self-control and every virtue. And therefore if these have not entirely scoured and washed away their iniquity in the cleansing process, they are in a moderate and halfway degree purged.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="230"><p> Esau’s words to his

father seem to have a like meaning: “Hast thou one blessing, my father? bless me also, O my father”
(Gen. xxvii. 38). For different blessings should be set apart for different persons: perfect blessings for the perfect, half-way for the imperfect, just as we find with men’s bodies: for the healthy and the sick require different exercises and different diet, and in all other matters which affect their way of living the same treatment is impossible. The healthy need what agrees with them to prevent their falling sick at all, and the sick need what fits their condition to bring them round to better health.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="231"><p> Since then the



<pb n="263"/>

goods which nature has to bestow are many, grant me, O Lord, that which befits me in Thy sight, though it be but the smallest, looking to one thing only, that the gift be such as I can bear with ease, not one that slight as it is will bring me, poor weakling, fainting to the ground.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="232"><p> And what do we suppose is

meant by the words, “Shall not the hand of the Lord suffice?” (Num. xi. 23). Surely this, that the powers of the Existent reach everywhere to benefit not only the highly placed but also those of lowlier reputation. And on these He bestows what befits them, according to the soul-measurements and appraisements of each, measuring and appraising in Himself
<note n="5.263.a">Or (reading ἰσότητι &lt;τῇ&gt; παρ᾽ ἑαυτῷ) “the equality inherent in Himself.”</note>
  by the rule of equality the due proportion to each.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="233"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="41"/> I am profoundly struck by the law enacted

for those who put off their sins and appear to be repentant. It bids them bring first as the victim a ewe without blemish, but “if his hand,” it continues,
“have not strength for a sheep, he shall bring for the sin which he has committed two turtledoves or two young pigeons, one for sin and one for a burnt offering.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="234"><p> But if his hand does not find a pair of turtledoves

or two young pigeons, he shall bring for his gift fine flour the tenth of an ephah. He shall not pour upon it oil, nor put upon it frankincense, because it is a sin offering, and shall bring it to the priest, and the priest shall take from it a complete handful and lay the memorial upon the altar”
(Lev. v.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="235"><p> 7 ff.). Moses, then, employs for propitiation

the three methods of repentance here mentioned, beasts or birds or wheaten flour, adapted doubtless


<pb n="265"/>

to the capacity of the penitent who is purified, for small things do not need great, nor great things small purifications, but such as are like and equal on the principle of proportion.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="236"><p> Why then there


should be three ways of repentance is worth inquiry. Practically cases both of sinning and of achieving righteousness fall into three classes, thoughts and words and deeds. And therefore in his Exhortations Moses, when he is shewing that the acquisition of the good is neither impossible nor hard to pursue, says,
</p></div><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="237"><p>
“You need not fly up to heaven nor go to the ends

of earth and sea to lay hold of it, but near and very near (and with the next words he shews the nearness as it were almost visible to the eye) is every work to thy mouth and heart and hands “(Deut. xxx. 12 ff.). In these three words he figures words, thoughts and intentions, deeds.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="238"><p> For good thinking and intending, good speaking and good doing make up, he means, human happiness just as their opposites make up unhappiness, since achievement of righteousness and

sinning are found in all these three places, heart, mouth and hand. For indeed some think and intend with excellent judgement and speak what is best and do what they should do. Of the three wrong thinking and intending is the least serious, and actually carrying out injustice is the most serious, while saying what we should not stands midway between the two.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="239"><p> Yet in practice the least serious proves to

be the most difficult to rid ourselves from, for it is a hard matter to bring to a standstill the soul’s changing movements. Their irresistible stream is such that we could sooner stem the rush of a torrent, for thoughts



<pb n="267"/>

after thoughts in countless numbers pour on like a huge breaker and drive and whirl and upset its whole being with their violence.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="240"><p> This then is


the best and most perfect form of purification, never even to admit any heinous thoughts, but to live with our fellow-citizens in peace and law observance, that order of which justice is the guiding influence. And the second best is to abstain from sinfulness of word, either by lying or perjury or subtlety or calumny, and in general from aiming at the ruin of others by giving a free rein to the mouth and tongue which it were better to bridle and bind with chains of adamant.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="241"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="42"/> It is easy to see why


wrong-speaking is a graver matter than wrong-thinking. A man’s thoughts are sometimes not due to himself, but come without his will. He is compelled to admit ideas on subjects which he has no wish to consider, and where there is no will no blame is due.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="242"><p> But speaking is voluntary, so that if a man

gives utterance to language which offends, he is wronging others, unhappy in this, that even when there is an opportunity of speaking something of a kinder nature he is not willing to use it. Such a person would do best to court complete freedom from disturbance,
<note n="5.267.a">Or “silence.” See App. p. 592.</note>
  and if he has not this freedom he can surely if he wills it keep silence.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="243"><p> But


the unjust action is a more grievous sin than any speaking, for the word is the shadow of the act,
<note n="5.267.b">See App. p. 592.</note>
  men say, and if the shadow be harmful, the act must be more harmful. And therefore Moses exempts mere intention from accusation and penalty. He knew that it was largely subject to involuntary changes and swervings, and rather the passive victim of the thoughts which flock into it than an active agent.

<pb n="269"/>

But all that issues through the mouth he requires to make its defence and stand its trial on the principle that our speech is in our own power.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="244"><p> But in these

trials words are judged more leniently, culpable actions more severely, for he appoints great penalties for the authors of great misdeeds, those who carry into actual execution what their ill-intended intentions have planned or their reckless tongues have uttered.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="245"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="43"/> For the purgation of these three, thought,

speech and action, he has named the sheep, the pair of doves or pigeons and the tenth of an ephah, the sacred measure, of fine flour, holding that thought should be purged with the sheep, speech with the birds, action with the fine flour. Why?</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="246"><p> Because just as

the mind is the best element in us, so the sheep takes the same place among the unreasoning animals considered as a whole, in virtue of its superior gentleness and the annual produce which it raises by itself, to benefit men and adorn them at the same time. For raiment averts mischief from frost and heat, and by veiling what nature would have hidden promotes decency in the wearers.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="247"><p>  Let us take then


the best animal, the sheep, as representing in a figure the purging of our best part, the mind, and similarly the birds as representing speech. For speech is light and winged by nature, moving swifter than an arrow, and flashing its way in every direction. For the word once spoken cannot return, but when carried outside races at a high speed, strikes the ears, and passing right through the whole region of hearing straightway turns into sound.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="248"><p>  Also

speech is twofold, partly true and partly false, and thence I think its comparison to a pair of doves or

<pb n="271"/>

pigeons. Moses directs that one bird should serve as a sin offering, and that the other should be offered by fire in its entirety, because it is a condition of true speech that it is entirely holy and perfect while false speech is the product of sin and needs reformation.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="249"><p>The fine flour is, as I have said, the symbol

of action, for it is a condition of flour that it is not brought into a pure state without art and contrivance but is sifted by the hands of corn-grinders, who have made a practice of this process. It accords with this when he says: “The priest shall take a complete handful and offer its memorial”—by the handful bringing out the thought of handiwork and action.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="250"><p> And he makes a very careful contrast in

speaking of the beasts and the birds. Of the first he says “If his hand be not strong enough for the sheep,” and of the second “If his hand do not find.”
Why is this? Because it needs great strength and a very high degree of power to suppress the changing movements of the mind, but it needs no great might to restrain trespasses of speech.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="251"><p> For against trespasses

committed with the voice there is a remedy as I have said before in quietude, of which everyone can easily avail himself, though many through their loquacity and measureless chattering do not find any limit to put upon their words.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="252"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="44"/> These and similar ways of analysing and

distinguishing things become familiar to the man of virtue through breeding and practice, and does it not therefore seem natural that he should pray that Ishmael may live, if he cannot as yet be the parent
<note n="5.271.a">κυοφορῆσαι rather strangely used for γεννᾶν. Has ἀρετή fallen out?</note>
  of Isaac? What then does God in His kindness do?</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="253"><p>

Abraham had asked for one thing, God gives him two.

<pb n="273"/>

He had prayed for the less, God grants him the greater. He said to him, we read, “Yes, Sarah thy wife shall bear a son “(Gen. xvii. 19). How significant is that answer “Yes,” fraught as it is with inner meaning. For what can be more befitting to God than to grant and promise His blessings in a moment and with a sign of assent?</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="254"><p> Yet those who receive a

sign of assent from God are refused assent by every fool. Thus the oracles represent Leah as hated and for this reason she received such a name.
<note n="5.273.a">See note on <hi rend="italic">De Cher.</hi> 41.</note>
  For by interpretation it means “rejected and weary,” because we all turn away from virtue and think her wearisome, so little to our taste are the commands she often lays upon us.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="255"><p> But from the Ruler of all she was awarded

such acceptance that her womb which He opened received the seed of divine impregnation (Gen. xxix. 31), whence should come the birth of noble practices and deeds. Learn then, soul of man, that
Sarah also, that is virtue, shall bear thee a son, as well as Hagar, the lower instruction. For Hagar’s offspring is the creature of teaching, but Sarah’s learns from none other at all than itself.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="256"><p> And wonder

not that God, who brings about all good things, has brought into being this kind also, and though there be few such upon earth, in Heaven vast is their number. You may learn this truth from the other elements, out of which man is constituted. Have the eyes been taught to see, do the nostrils learn to smell, do the hands touch or the feet advance in obedience to the orders or exhortations of instructors?</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="257"><p> As for

our impulses and mental pictures, which are the primal conditions of the soul, according as it is in motion or at rest, are they made what they are by


<pb n="275"/>

teaching? Does our mind attend the school of the professor of wisdom and there learn to think and to apprehend? All these exempt from teaching make use of self-worked independent nature for their respective activities.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="258"><p> Why then need you still wonder

that God showers virtue without toil or trouble, needing no controlling hand but perfect and complete from the very first? And if you would have further testimony of this can you find any more trustworthy than Moses, who says that while other men receive their food from earth, the nation of vision alone has it from heaven?</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="259"><p> The earthly food is produced with

the co-operation of husbandmen, but the heavenly is sent like the snow by God the solely self-acting, with none to share his work. And indeed it says “Behold I rain upon you bread from heaven” (Ex. xvi.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="260"><p> 4). Of what food can he rightly say that it is rained from heaven, save of heavenly wisdom which is sent from

above on souls which yearn for virtue by Him who sheds the gift of prudence in rich abundance, whose grace waters the universe, and chiefly so in the holy seventh (year) which he calls the Sabbath?
<note n="5.275.a">Wendland gives the reference for this as Ex. xvi. 23 ff. But this can hardly be right, as no manna fell on the Sabbath. The reference is clearly to the Sabbatical year of Lev. xxv. 4, 5, definitely called “Sabbath,” on which he has dwelt in <hi rend="italic">De Fug.</hi> 170 ff. ἡ ἑβδόμη seems to be used for ἑβδομάς in <hi rend="italic">De Decal.</hi> 159 and <hi rend="italic">De Spec. Leg.</hi> ii. 40, as well as in § 144 above. Presumably no noun but ἡμέρα can be understood, but by frequent use it has come to be a noun, which Philo can extend to cover any sacred period, day, month, or year.</note>
  For then he says there will be a plentiful supply of good things spontaneous and self-grown, which even all the art in the world could never raise, but springing up and bearing their proper fruit through self-originated, self-consummated nature.

<pb n="277"/>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="261"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="45"/> Virtue then shall bear thee a true-born,

male child, one free from all womanish feelings, and thou shalt call his name by the feeling which he raises in thee, which feeling is most surely joy. And therefore thou shalt give him a name significant of joy, even laughter.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="262"><p> Just as fear and grief have their own

special ejaculations, which the overpowering force of emotion coins, so moods of happy planning or of gladness compel us to break out into natural utterances, as aptly and exactly expressing our meaning as any which an adept in the study of names could devise.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="263"><p> Therefore he says: “I have blessed him, I

will increase and multiply him: he shall beget twelve nations (that is, the whole round and train of the early branches of the professional schools), but my covenant will I establish with Isaac “(Gen. xvii. 20 f.). Thus both forms of virtue, one where the teacher is another, one where teacher and learner are the same, will be open to human kind. And where man is weak he will claim the former, where he is strong the latter which comes ready to his hands.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="264"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="46"/> “But at this season,” he continues, “she shall

bear to thee,” that is, wisdom shall bear joy. What is the season you set before us, Master? Wonder of wonders! Is it not the season which is as no other, which no created being can set forth? For the true season, the dayspring of the universe, when all is well and seasonable with earth and heaven, and the intermediate natures, both living creatures and plants, can be no other than Himself.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="265"><p> And therefore Moses

feared not to say to the fugitives from danger who shrank from waging the war for virtue against their antagonists, “The season hath departed from them, but the Lord is among you “(Num. xiv. 9).
<note n="5.277.a"><hi rend="italic">Cf. De Post.</hi>122, where however the καιρός is the false god who deserts his votaries.</note>
  Here he

<pb n="279"/>

acknowledges with hardly any disguise that God is the Season which departs far away from all the impious, but walks in rich and fertile souls.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="266"><p> “For I will

walk among you,” he says, “and will be your God”
(Lev. xxvi. 12). But they who say that season means the changes of the year strain the terms from their proper meaning, for they have not carefully studied the real natures of things but are deeply tainted with looseness of thought.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="267"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="47"/> He goes on to say—thereby heightening

the glory of the child to be—that he will be born “in the other year “(Gen. xvii. 21). And by other year he does not mean an interval of time which is measured by the revolutions of sun and moon, but something truly mysterious, strange and new, other than the realm of sight and sense, having its place in the realm of the incorporeal and intelligible, and to it belongs the model and archetype of time, eternity or aeon.
<note n="5.279.a">From <hi rend="italic">Timaeus</hi> 37 D, as also in <hi rend="italic">Quis Rerum</hi> 165, <hi rend="italic">Quod</hi> <hi rend="italic">Deus</hi> 32, where see note.</note>
  The word aeon signifies the life of the world of thought, as time is the life of the perceptible.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="268"><p> In

this same year, too, is “the hundredfold crop of barley found “(Gen. xxvi. 12) by him who sows the gifts of God to produce an increase of blessings, and thereby increases to the uttermost the number of those who shall deservedly partake of it. But note that the sower generally reaps.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="269"><p> Yet he, though he

sowed, and thereby displayed the virtue which hates envy and vice, is not said to reap but to find. For He who ripened the ear of His benefits and filled it with corn was Another, even He who prepares and matures higher hopes and more abundant bounties and puts them forth to be found by those who seek.

<pb n="281"/>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="270"><p><milestone unit="para"/><milestone unit="altchapter" n="48"/> The words “he completed talking to

him” (Gen. xvii. 22) are equivalent to “He perfected the hearer himself,” who before was devoid of wisdom, and filled him with thoughts that cannot die. And when the learner had become perfect, “the Lord went up from Abraham,” says Moses (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>). He does not mean that Abraham was parted from Him, for by his very nature the sage is God’s attendant, but he wished to shew the independence of the learner. His purpose is that when the superintendence of the master is withdrawn, and no compulsion is applied, the pupil may make an exhibition of his own powers, and shewing a diligence which is voluntary and self-imposed may work out by his own efforts what he has learnt. For it is the way of a teacher to give his pupil opportunity of independent practice without suggestions from himself, and thus set upon him the stamp of indelible memory in its surest form.

</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>
